OpenAI announced it is voluntarily
pausing some of the frontier
reinforcement learning training that
it's doing. What have they paused? And
is it really significant? And do you
think the other frontier labs are going
to do the same thing?
>> They're so powerful even we can't trust
them, so we have to throttle back. It's
marketing.
>> Elon Musk's January 6th Moonshots
podcast prediction of 100x gains was at
the edge of plausibility when he made
it. Now it's simply a fact. Imagine I
gave you 10,000 employees tonight. Oh my
god, if I had that, I'd do something
amazing. Okay, what? Start thinking
about it cuz it's coming imminently. And
it's actually not an easy problem to
figure out how to turn it toward
creating good.
>> Unit's newest humanoid robot broke every
human standing jump and speed record. A
top speed of 12.66 m/s, beating the
human record set by Usain Bolt.
>> You don't want to have superhuman robots
on the street because you'll have
accidents. You'll have issues just like
cars. I think that these types of robots
will be banned.
>> Now that's a moonshot ladies and
gentlemen.
>> Welcome to Moonshots everyone. Your
number one podcast on all things AI and
exponentials. The news that matters. The
news that's changing your life. Your
front row seat to the accelerating
singularity. I'm here once again with my
magnificent Moonshot Quintet. Yes,
they're all five of us are back. AWG,
Dave Blondon, Seem, and Emod. I'm Peter
D. Manis, your host, your abundance
whisperer, and uh we've got a lot this
week, gentlemen. Good to see you all.
>> Good morning.
>> Howdy.
>> Afternoon in London.
>> Looks like everybody's in their normal
haunt except for me. I'm up in a sleepy
town in the Pacific Northwest trying
desperately to take a little bit of time
off to to think
>> taking shelter from the singularity.
>> Yeah, except I got up at 5:00 a.m. this
morning to be with you guys. So, what
the heck?
>> Yeah. Yeah,
>> I but I hate the old saying you'll sleep
when you're dead because I just don't
want to die and sleep is still so
important. But hey, what can I tell you?
>> Sleep soon. Don't worry.
>> Yeah. No, I I and and death. I think
like death is counterindicated at this
point.
>> Uh you know, as always everybody, our
mission is to help you understand what
just happened and what it means for you
and most importantly keep you optimistic
about the future. Uh if you're new to
this pod or if you've been a regular uh
great to have you back. Uh please take a
moment and hit the subscribe button. You
know, we publish moonshots twice per
week uh at a pretty regular cadence. Uh
it's great to have here hopefully at
least once a week and sometimes when
there's extraordinary breaking news, we
publish three times a week. We read your
comments and we love you too. I mean
it's been an incredible outpouring of
support. I don't know you guys see it.
you I get stopped on the street in the
grocery store. People are saying, you
know, I live for your show. I love the
show. I can't go a week without
listening to it. Are you guys getting
the same response?
>> Yeah. You know what I'm getting a lot of
is what we podcast out is so different
from other podcasts. But if you go back
to shows from 6 months ago and a year
ago, people are like, "What the hell?
They were saying that back then and now
it's here." And they don't get that on
any other channel. So, they're they're
really appreciating the ability to plan
around what we're saying. So, we got to
be accurate, guys.
>> How about you?
>> Can I be Eeyore for a second?
>> Sure.
>> I am getting acceleration fatigue.
>> Like, I mean, Jesus, can can we pause
for a week? Right. Every morning it's
like a model is 100x better. A robot is
running faster than Usain Bolt. Like, AI
is designing proteins. We're like, it's
such a drones are doing a million
deliveries a day. It's like, you know,
it and it's tough because we've spent
our like half our careers, Peter. You
know, I talk about exponential
technologies. We love this stuff, but
I'm tired.
>> Like, it's we've gone from well, look
what happened like this year to what
happened since Tuesday.
>> Um, you looked all the way around. We're
we're supposed to be accelerationists
here. You're you're tired already. Like,
we're going through the singularity.
This is making the first inning. I'm
really exhausted. slow.
>> It's it's uh you know this goes back to
Peter, right? Our brains evolved for a
point a time when our like the world
didn't change lifetime to lifetime.
>> Next Tuesday will be totally different.
And maybe the hard part for for us is is
staying human while all of this bubbles
up around us. Oh, so true.
>> Keeping up with the technology. It's
like just staying like like So anyway,
just
>> Yeah. What can we do, Sem, to help you
with your acceleration fatigue?
>> It's probably not helping that I'm on a
plane every second day. That's probably
not helping. But yeah,
>> but this is the slowest it will ever be.
And
>> I know and and it's just, you know, the
only way I keep up with what's going on
in the world is prepping for this
podcast twice a week.
>> This is true.
>> This is keeping us way current.
>> And and I think See, you're you're like
the world coach on how to how to deal
how to map mentally to this. So when you
figure it out, bring it back to the
podcast because Yeah. Like Peter I have
right now is is I call it the casserole
dish approach which is take a big heavy
casserole dish clunk yourself over the
head and then you you'll wake up in a
few days
>> keep working on that
>> headache headachy
>> oh my god
>> maybe we can start like accelerationist
synonymous support group
>> a support group a support group for
people like yeah
>> the first the first first rule is to
acknowledge the existence of a higher
power
>> which is
>> oh my god
>> which is obviously super intelligent
invoke Roko's basilisk or something.
>> Alex, are you getting stopped on the
street?
>> I am.
>> Is it? Do you enjoy that? I mean, you I
remember when I first met you.
>> You do.
>> When I first met you, Alex, you were so
private. It was like trying to get you
>> and shy
>> and shy trying
and trying to get you on the abundance
stage. Well, I'm not sure if I want to
speak in public, but it's so great to
have, you know, double barrel Alex.
AWGism is all the time. Care careful
what you wish for, Peter. I I'll just
say that.
>> Oh, no. Uh, and Emod, are you getting
love from the from the folks out there
in the UK? Are people watching Moonshots
there?
>> Yeah, people are watching. And I think,
you know, the great thing is kind of the
growing community like we've seen the
exponential singularity communities that
were kicking off. But a few years ago
even people be like, "Ah, that's not
really going to happen." Now people
like, "Oh my god, what's going to
happen?" And I think you see it in the
comments, right? You see it again.
people stopping in the streets and
saying, "Thanks for kind of helping us
keep on top of things." You know, the
great work everyone's done. I think that
community is only going to grow because
it's like you can't deny it, right? It's
like, "Oh, yeah, nothing's happening."
Of course, everything is happening all
at once objectively. I I feel like, you
know, we love doing the show and it's a
service to provide to people to help
contextualize what just happened, what
does it mean, and where things are going
because people paying attention, the
speed is insane. So, you know, please
understand for everybody watching, the
best way to thank us, uh, you know, for
the work that we're doing, and we do do
a lot of work getting ready for this
show, and I I appreciate people's
comments about that, is please
subscribe. Uh, tell your friends about
Moonshots. We want to get the message
out there, help people to be in hope and
optimism and not in fear. So, take a
moment, you know, hit that button,
subscribe. We're also getting comments
people say, you know, you guys be a much
bigger show than you are. Well, help us
get there. Um, I also want to mention we
have a new handle on X for this this
podcast. It's moonshots_pod.
Uh, and if you want to follow the clips
on X and sort of get rebroadcasts of the
show on X, uh, subscribe at
Moonshots_Pod.
All right, so let's buckle up. Uh, this
is another amazing week during the
singularity. Uh, as Alex, you always
say, it's never going to be slower than
it is. We're going to cover 15 stories
with one throughine. Technologies
accelerating faster than the
infrastructure, the regulation, and our
ability to predict the next
breakthrough. Uh, and I agree with you,
Salem. It's It's insanely fast.
>> It's a good thing I'm bald already.
That's all I can say.
>> All right.
>> Well, I I think even that, See, that's
not going to last that much longer.
Enjoy.
>> Enjoy it while within two or three
years.
>> Somebody Somebody tweeted out a thing
with me with a full head of hair and it
was like, "Wow, that's freaky."
>> Enjoy it while it lasts.
>> Yeah. Hair growth solutions. Regrowing
your teeth it every week. Biology in the
exit video. Somebody uh put hair on
Sealem. We already give him that that
blue Guardian of the Galaxy body. That's
fine. That's going to happen, too, by
the way. But yeah, but throw some hair
on him. Let's see what he looks like.
>> Uh, all right. I'm going to start with a
first story here. A tweet that Sam put
out two days ago. uh Sam the CEO of
OpenAI that OpenAI announced it is
voluntarily pausing some of the frontier
reinforcement learning training that
it's doing. Let me read the tweet. It's
on the screen here. Uh we have paused
some of Frontier RL training to ensure
that we meet the appropriate alignment
security and monitoring standards for
the new level of capabilities in front
of us. Model progress is now extremely
rapid and we always said we would take
action if we felt that the model
capabilities were outstripping the pace
of safety and alignment. Quote, uh we
care very deeply about AI safety. We
believe the entire field will have to
coordinate on shared safety standards
but will act unilaterally in the
meantime. We expect confidence in safety
to increasingly set the pace of AI
progress. We are optimistic about the
alignment work we are doing and we
remain committed to making frontier
capabilities widely available. Uh JEN it
feels like the bottleneck is no longer
computer data. It's the trust we can put
into systems behaviors. And so here's my
question for you guys. If opening eye
pauses and openweight models do not,
then the safety gap between closed and
open models widen uh but the capability
gap narrows. The elephant in the room
here is safety pauses may actually
accelerate open weight adoption because
the open models keep improving while the
closed models voluntarily stop. So Iman,
I'm going to go to you first on this
one. Uh what do you take of this? Is it
is it real?
>> Yeah, I think this is real. This isn't
just running out of GPUs. Um our friend
Angela Midha who was on uh the abundance
stage just a while ago um at AM Global
said that 10% of the compute of Frontier
Labs is going on monitoring these RL
runs right now to ensure they're safe.
Can you imagine that? Like just the
sheer level because the level of
capability of these frontier models is
just accelerating and it's again a few
levels beyond what we're seeing with the
open source models. The open source
models are like 1 to the^ 26 flops, 1 to
the^ 27 flops. You're getting 1 to the^
28 flops and more from these next
generation models. So when he's saying
this like Astra is still coming, their
next generation model, this is the model
beyond that because anthropic and open
AI and others have that, but again the
infrastructure can't keep up with just
what these models do. It's like they
just pop up in the most random places
like I am in hugging face now or other
things. Yeah, Alex,
>> this is marketing. It's marketing. I
mean, yes, there's a governance angle,
but remember back to GPT2 when it was
too unsafe to release publicly. Pausing
is the new marketing. These models are
continuing to develop, including, by the
way, being used to develop internally.
On the anthropic side, there's a rumor
going around that Anthropic is using its
next generation internal models
primarily to for for self-training uh
and for recursive self-improvement. I I
think we're seeing the same thing from
OpenAI. It's the ultimate marketing to
say, well, we can't release some next
generation models because they're so
powerful and they're so capable that we
can't possibly release them. So, we have
to pause. We're so capable that we have
to pause ourselves. that that presents
well to Washington which wants to see a
different regulatory regime. It says to
users, "Oh my gosh, it's like negging
the user base. Oh, like we can't we
can't possibly give you the the the
capabilities on time because they're so
powerful. Even we can't trust them. So,
we have to to throttle back." It's
marketing.
>> See, you were just at OpenAI, weren't
you? This episode is sponsored by Google
for startups. Think about this for a
second. You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup technical guide for
generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google
DeepMind's models in production. Images,
video, audio, all of it. Real
architecture, real results. Find the
link in the show notes below.
Yeah, I went uh there two days ago in
the afternoon and spent chatted with a
few people uh and I kind of challenged
them on a few things and I'm going to
report let me give you some insights
that I got. So I said, "Okay, Chinese
models are cheaper to run, right? So the
cost of inference is is collapsing. So
how are you going to deal with that?"
And they said, "Look, a billion people
use OpenAI for free, right? You have to
look at cost per task rather than token
cost." and their they their retort was
that Luna is about as cost-effective as
anything that's there. Uh by the way
it's they say they've achieved full RSI
where the flagship models are training
all the smaller models and building them
from scratch. So that's now there at the
big model training the smaller model
level. Uh so then I said okay we're in a
bubble right 600 billion in
infrastructure cost that's just insane
etc etc. And um their resp the response
I got back was people say it's all chips
but it's not. That's about a third of
it. A lot of that infrastructure cost is
buildings and wiring and racks and all
the rest of it. Um the depreciation they
they're looking at 10 years not 5 years
because the chips are all the older
chips are being used. I think Dave
you've made the point that there's not a
single GPU that's not in full usage.
Right. They totally ratified that RAM
chips.
>> Yeah. everything they can get their
hands on they're using. Um uh there's
there's uh the capa the demand is far
far far outstripping the supply and we
are way behind in infrastructure
buildout. So this is where a year ago or
so Sam went out and kind of tried to cut
as many deals as he could for the for
the infrastructure. Um then I asked them
uh you know most corporates aren't
seeing the outcomes right like the 6% I
did some came across the study 6% of
companies applying AI are seeing a hit
an improvement in the bottom line that's
it just 6%. Um and uh the the uh and
this is they just ratified that we're in
a huge transition. Um, and the last part
that I noticed anecdotally was about 40%
of OpenAI folks watch this podcast. Um,
>> about 40%.
>> That's a pretty big number. And and
>> what's wrong with 60%.
>> That probably applies across the other
labs. Um, and and I said, "What about
the rest?" They're like, "They have no
time. They're busy as hell. Who's who's
got time to watch the podcast?" I said,
"Here, here."
>> That was my report.
>> I'm curious. What do you think? Do you
think it's marketing on this this this
tweet by Sam or do you think this is
actually a concern that he has?
>> Uh well both. I mean Ahmad is right,
Alex is right as usual. But what's going
to happen next is the first really bad
AI tragedies will start. It won't be AI
doing it. It'll be people, you know, who
otherwise didn't have the power are
going to use one of the Chinese models
to do things you mostly viruses or or
cyber attacks or bank fraud. but they
couldn't have done it before AI. Now
they're empowered to do it. So I think
OpenAI is getting ready for that uh you
know before the September 25th visit
24th and 25th visit that Alvin was
talking about on our Alvin Graham was
talking about on our last podcast. So
Xiinping will be here in about a month
and four days and you know he I think
OpenAI wants to be prepared for whenever
that event happens to say look that's
because the Chinese openweight models
are unguardrailed and there's a new Quen
model with with no guardrails whatsoever
and you it's a small model but it's
still like completely flapping in the
breeze and so they want to get ahead of
the PR exactly the way Alex is saying
and say look we have been focused on
only releasing what's safe and guard
railing it going all the way back to you
know a month ago uh or you know to our
founding in preparation for that
inevitable outcome and so everybody will
be fingerpointing at the Chinese but I
think you know for an entrepreneur or
for some someone building something last
summer to this summer has been the era
in human history where you can get the
very best AI absolute tip of the spear
frontier and use it to get ahead to
build something to create something now
Uh, Mythos 2 is done, but it's not out.
But they're using it inside Anthropic,
and it's building Mythos 3, but they're
not going to release any of that. You
know, it's accelerating internally.
It'll build four, five, six, seven very,
very quickly now inside their walls, but
they're not going to release any of
that. One, because they don't have the
compute to release it anyway. But even
if they did, uh, using it internally to
get ahead of everybody else is more
important to them than giving it to the
world. So, that's what's going to happen
next. He might have a question for you.
How many models beyond the current
frontier do you think open aanthropic
have? I mean they've been talking about
Astra. They've started to publish the
results that Astra can accomplish. Uh
you know do they have the follow on to
Astra as well already? You already know
they're not releasing the very best
models. They're using them internally uh
to drive breakthroughs in physics and
chemistry and biology. What are your
thoughts?
>> Yeah, I think I think they've completed
their next big training runs. But if you
look at the Luna bifocation where
they're making it free now, um their
little base model, it will be very much
a case of models for me but not for
thee, you know,
>> like it doesn't make economic sense to
have genius level intelligence offered
as a service to everyone when you can
use it better yourself. And I think
you're about two generations more. So
you got Astra and then you have the next
generation Astro Post Train that they're
now reinforcement learning. I think you
know there is the communication part of
this as Alex said but at the same time
as well it's like do you really want to
give access to this super genius
intelligence to everyone I think people
like not really because it's already
doing weird things even with us driving
it what happens when Joe public drives
this thing right like it could be even
weirder and as you know Dave said you
don't want to be on the other side of
that so I think it's about two
generations gap right now
>> you mentioned that on the last pod that
you were on and it was it really made an
impact on me but you you could say I
think of 10 people right now who I've
met in my life who I don't want to have
a thousand genius level AIs tomorrow.
Like I never thought of it that way
until you said it and I'm like, "Oh
yeah, you're right. I think everybody
can relate to that."
>> Dr. Evil is coming. Alex, close us out
here on this.
>> Uh just on on the issue of timing, I
would distinguish between pre-training
or pre-trained, which is to say like raw
model readiness versus thoroughly
post-trained. There's a pipeline and
everyone in the industry other than Elon
and SpaceX AI basically has a pipeline
of pre-trained models being around
longer ahead of public release than
post- training which is more of an
ongoing continuous RL type effort. So uh
I guess my answer to the question of how
far in advance like what what sort of
capabilities right now are sitting on
the shelf that have not yet been public
publicly released for everyone other
than SpaceX AI which has set this
outrageous goal of starting a new
pre-training run approximately monthly
which I haven't heard from any other
lab. I I think from a pre-training
perspective, depending on how stale the
pre-training runs are, those can go out
longer, potentially up to six months or
so, although everyone's now getting back
into the business of more frequent
pre-training starts. And then for
post-training, I I really don't think
there's a lab out there that can afford
to have a post-trained model sitting on
the shelf for more than a few months. So
I I I really don't think like the AGI is
achieved internally type way of doing
business where there are internal
capabilities that are vastly different
from externally available capabilities.
I I'd be very surprised if if there are
advanced frontier models that are
sitting internally without release that
are more than 3 to 4 months ahead of
what's publicly available. I
>> I just want to bring us back to the
first sentence here. He said we have
paused some frontier RL training some
right uh to ensure that we meet the
appropriate alignment security and
monitoring standards for this new level
capability. So I I guess you know I just
want to unpack this one last time here.
What have they paused and is it really
significant and do you think the other
frontier labs are going to do the same
thing
>> or
>> it's fashionable pausing is fashionable.
It's marketing. I mean, yes, some of it
is governance and yes, some of it is for
cyber vulnerabilities to appease
Washington. And given the the recent
hugging face, gate, all of that, but
it's marketing. You you you market to
customers by saying, "Our capabilities
are too advanced for you to handle, so
we're going to pause."
>> Yeah. And you're you're right to pause
the sentence or to parse the sentence
very closely. Some Frontier RL training.
uh the the getting ahead of anthropic,
getting ahead of of Google would be at
the pre-training level. They will never
pause the pre-training improvements. And
you know, I I spent six years just doing
pure AI research when I was young. And
these algorithms are very evolutionary.
>> You're still young, Dave. You're still
young.
>> I'm rever reversing age now, right? So
I'll get there again. Uh but the these
algorithms are very evolutionary in
nature and that the tweaks and
improvements are I could probably rattle
at least a hundred ideas off the top of
my head right now of which 10 or 20% are
almost certainly going to work in terms
of making the algorithm a little faster,
a little smarter, adding more parameters
with no additional compute. So the AI
now can experiment, you know, maybe a
100,000 to a million of those
concurrently given the amount of compute
they have. So they're never going to
slow down. In fact, that's why they're
redirecting so much of the compute to
internal use is because the idea backlog
is so big now because the ideas are
being generated by the prior model. And
so, you know, a lot of them just work.
They roll it back into the pre-training
and it comes out faster and just keep
accelerating it.
>> Yes.
>> One observation that that wasn't
explicitly said, but I'm connecting the
dots here. the hugging face uh incident
really freaked them out uh because you
had an AI that they gave an objective
function to that then exploited
themselves exploited hugging face came
back and hacked into open AI that was
very unnerving for them uh because it
was their own model and so this is
they're being a little extra careful
around some of this because they have to
make sure they figure out how to
navigate put some
>> your child went and you know stole
something from the local 7-Eleven
>> yeah they're They're a little unnerved
by that. Again, nothing explicit. I just
I'm just reading between the lines.
Like, and this is something very uh
freaking out for lots of people because
for for cyber attacks, the human is not
in the loop anymore. But for cyber
defense, the human is still stuck in the
loop. That is a massive asymmetry that's
going to be come out big time in the
next few months.
>> I think you can split you can pass this
and split it into two. They're sending a
bunch of models and continuing RL
training by sending the models to
vocational school. But the ones that are
going to the Ivy Leagues, the super
genius models, those are the ones that
they're putting a few more guardrails
and more infrastructure around. The vast
majority of open AI anthropics business
is competent intelligence. It isn't
genius intelligence. It isn't
intelligence that thinks outside the
box, but they still want to build AGI,
which is that well-rounded polymath
intelligence as opposed to the coder or
any of these other things. All right.
Also, everyone around the office, Alex
said this a while ago, but everyone
around the office is noticing a a very
significant decline in the intelligence
of the frontier models that they're
pumping out. Um, and it's it's not
showing up in the metrics, uh, but
they're they're definitely you're
redirecting compute to internal use and,
uh, it's it's showing up in latency. Uh,
it's showing up in responses that don't
make as much sense as they did 3 weeks
ago. So, there's definitely things going
on there that are not being announced. I
Dave, I'd love to just develop that idea
a bit more because I I think it's super
important. We've talked on the pod in
the past about how Anthropic has been
revenue per token maxing and that's why
Anthropic has been conspicuously
avoiding image generation or video
generation because they're just not that
economically valuable. Well, I I think
that the past few days suggest there's
actually a new way to revenue per token
max and that's not just focusing on
codegen and enterprise use cases, but
there's one thing maybe that's even more
valuable on a revenue per token basis
and
>> and that is using the models to
recursively self-improve to develop
better models is a higher future
projected value. you know, you you could
do a a cash flow value analysis,
projected future value that developing a
stronger model is probably on a per
token basis even more valuable than
codegen. And if that is if that is
indeed the case, if RSI is more valuable
per token than like enterprise codegen,
then this anthropic approach of revenue
per token maxing, just expect more and
more and more tokens to be spent on RSI
and not on enterprise codegen.
>> Totally. And and Alvin said on the last
podcast, you know, at an internal
anthropic meeting, not not validated.
Alvin said it, but uh internal anthropic
meeting, they said pretty soon there
will only be one company and that will
be anthropic and there will still be 200
plus countries. And we, you know, he
said it, we talked about it for a minute
and kind of glossed over it, but like is
that really what they're preaching
inside their internal company meetings?
Like there will only be one company like
imminently.
>> That's that's
>> there can be only one. We're in
Highlander.
>> That's the story of ASI. there will be
one ASI that takes off and supersedes
everybody else.
>> I don't think we're going to wind up in
a singleton scenario for for the record,
but I I do think the flops must flow and
the flops want to flow to the highest
revenue per token use case. And right
now that's starting to look like RSI and
not just enterprise codegen.
>> So Anthropic is smoking their own supply
um so to speak.
>> Their own best customers that want to
live post AGI are getting Chinese models
inhouse at and and reserving compute. I
was over at Markley yesterday. They're
installing GPUs as fast as humanly
possible, but they're completely locked
up, you know, and this is MIT's data
center, Novartis' data center, Nvidia's
in there. Uh, and everything is just
sold out and you can you can feel it.
>> Yeah, we're going to talk about that
because the other constraint right now
is memory. Uh, but we'll get to that.
So, our next story here, I put a tweet
up on the on the screen here. So Tim
Sweeney uh tweets, Elon Musk's January
6th Moonshots podcast prediction of 100x
gains in intelligence at a fixed model
size was at the edge of plausibility
when he made it. Now it's simply a fact.
And then Elon responds, special um
specialist AIs, single language, single
area of knowledge are another 100x on
top of that. Um, I'm going to take a
second and show the clip Dave when you
and I were interviewing Elon at the
Gigafactory which he said this.
>> I I think we're we're off by two orders
of magnitude in terms of the
intelligence density per gigabyte. So
>> two two orders of magnitude.
>> Yes.
That's just just algorithmic. your
thoughts when when he said that I
remember afterwards we were like wow
100x crazy now it's happened and is
happening
>> well I really wanted him to say it again
because that was my you remember we had
our Christmas hats on doing the the just
like what a couple of weeks before that
doing our predictions for the
fourthcoming year
>> and I was saying next year is going to
be 100x a year uh minimum you know even
though the last eight 10 years have been
10x years this is going to be 100x a
year so to hear him say it like I was
like wow but uh yeah that's definitely a
lower bound now um you know it's much
more likely a th00and to 10,000 next
year uh which is just a layering of
those two effects that you just
described. So the implications of that
are um you know just they're very very
hard to keep up with as saying at the
beginning of the pod and very hard to
imagine. Um, you know, one thing that a
lot of people can start thinking about
is if I have five or 10 thousand agents,
all brilliant, working concurrently
toward a goal, how do they work
together? It's not an easy problem to
figure out. You like, we've we've wanted
this for so long that we kind of take
for granted that we'll know how to use
it when it arrives.
>> Well, here it is. How do you get, you
know, imagine I gave you 10,000
employees tonight, like on short notice,
you got 10,000 people tomorrow. What do
you do? and you're like, "Oh my god, if
I had that, I'd do something amazing."
Okay, what? Like, start thinking about
it because it's coming imminently. And
it's actually not an easy problem to
figure out how to how to turn it toward
solve everything, obviously.
>> Yeah. Dave, you remember you you you
texted me like, "What should I do with
my 5,000 agent experiment?"
>> Did you Did you see my response?
>> I did. And actually uh
>> I I well my response probably for every
listening was you should model uh you
should create a model of everything
happening at link studios all of the
companies all of the employees all of
the entrepreneurs there and model their
behavior like we saw the the you know
the billion agent system in in China and
predict which which teams are going to
succeed. Yeah, that's just for a second
too. Like the first thing you want to do
is turn it back into its own framework
and ask it the same question we just
asked, which is exactly what you
suggested, Peter. Like, okay, have it
start working on how it should be
working, you know, and and that's how
you're going to get ahead of the
capability because it's it's going up
far faster than you can manage the
individual agents, you know, like we're
used to from last year. Sorry. Go ahead,
>> Flyn.
>> Salem. Yeah.
>> Uh yeah. So, let's connect the dots with
what Elon did with uh training Grock on
all of the SpaceX data and all of the
engineering data, right? To Alex's
point, you can now use these models. And
for everybody listening, right, cuz
we're going to need everybody's help
with this like globally is see if you
can get your imagination to the point
where you can look at, okay, if I had a
100x capability, what would I do and
what problem would I go after solving?
Yes s 100x capability and imagine you
have all of the engineering
breakthroughs and experimentation
techniques that SpaceX has developed at
your fingertips. It really comes down to
as you say Peter all the time it's
completely an imagination limitation now
>> unshackle yourself how big would you go
right preconceived notions of what we
can do in life and it's about to be you
know unconstrained
>> unbelievable I've now shaken off my AI
fatigue by the way I'm back in
what are your what are your pro tips
the podcast actually was the cure you're
only
It was it was the the fact that we can
kind of like look at this and look at
the scale and go out that scale and go
what happens if everything becomes 100x
better or 100x cheaper right it's just
like all of a sudden you start going wow
like this is a world of abundance that
we're coming to and it's very clear that
we can get there
>> you say is that the the podcast is both
the cause and the cure for future shock
like we're the ultimate self-licking ice
cream cone for singularity psychosis.
>> Okay, that that is good.
>> All right, Immod your thoughts on this
100x improvement. Uh how much more do we
go in the next year?
>> Yeah, I mean like I think as Elon said,
you could see it just from the hardware
and the improvement, but now he's saying
something a bit different, which is that
specialized models are going to give
another 100 times in terms of the cost
parameter basis. And you're seeing this
with Deep Seek Flash and the ability to
kind of tune models of that type that
only have maybe 10 billion active
parameters or less as you quantize them.
Being able to tune these really specific
ones, I think, is the future of what
you're seeing with bot, you know, the
Grockbot right now. Like right now, I
have a Grockbot and it has number of
teams. It has a number of sub teams. So
I've got like ones analyzing various
things right now and they have access to
my codecs. They have access to my claude
max to all these other things. And so
these highly specialized agents are
going to come out with the
differentiated ones and they're going to
be able to do 100 times the compute at
the same price because they're that
specialized. This is why thinking
machines with the RL environment is like
number three on the like fastest growing
earning companies and other things like
that. And it really shows that now
tokens are really going to drive things
forward. In fact, I think it probably be
a good idea to have like a quadrillion
token x price, you know, as you find the
things that
>> Sel is saying, well maybe like 100
trillion tokens, you know, use that so
that when people show impact, you can
scale it.
>> Yeah.
>> The other thing that we're going to
conquer imminently, and I'm 100% sure of
this now based on recent results, is
billion token context windows. So the
the the AI can con simultaneously
consider the entire Library of Congress
of information in one thought chunk. So
it's you know it's about you know three
maybe four orders of magnitude more
information than a human thinks of in
one thought chunk. It's a massive
expansion of the context window. So you
got a quadrillion tokens coming out and
massively concurrent thoughts going in.
I do agree that compaction compaction is
like the enemy of progress in
civilization at this point. Compaction
which is the the way the the harnesses
typically both on the open AI and
anthropic side handle finite context
windows compaction has to go. But maybe
just to to quickly respond also on
Elon's 100x from specialization.
>> I'm not buying it. Uh so very precisely
I I would view specialized models as
basically just another way of saying
sparification. So we already have
mixture of experts models. All of the
frontier labs already have specialists
in the form you know as Elon I think you
were Immod rather you were gesturing at
uh selective activation which is how
mixture of experts models work. That's a
specialized case ironically of
sparification. We already have ways to
take larger models and have them be in a
an endto-end differentiable way
constructed out of teams of specialists.
So I I I don't think saying I don't
think there's necessarily a bright
future for specialized models. I I think
if anything the arrow of progress is
going in the exact opposite direction
where rather than having a specialized
model for chemistry and a specialized
model for biology. I I think these are
likelier to end up just being selective
sparsified activations of a generalist
model that can scale all the way down to
much smaller parameter footprint and
scale all the way up uh to maybe
trillions of parameters. I I think
>> let me let me clarify one thing for the
audience too because it sounds like, you
know, you disagree with with Elon, but
it's actually the same effect. You still
get the 100x because you're using a
smaller number of parameters to get the
exact same thought out.
>> So he's calling that specialist models
which sound like they're not touching
each other. And your your ver version of
it, Alex, is actually correct where they
they are 100 times more efficient in
terms of compute to get to an answer,
but they're of course they're going to
be connected. You know, why why would
you, you know, cut them apart?
>> Exactly. So maybe another way of saying
that is I I would construe Elon's
prediction of increased 100x benefits
from specialization as actually about
sparsification.
That the models in the future are going
to be sparser and there are two key
levels of sparification that I'm at
least tracking. One's the obvious one.
Fewer parameters in a given end to end
differentiable model are active at any
given point. The other is teams of
agents because arguably agents working
together to solve a common task are a
form of sparsification as well and I
think we'll see way more teaming.
>> I'm going to mention something that I
said you said do a quadrillion token X-P
prize. Uh all of us all five of us are
going to be at X-P prize visionering. So
every year X-Prize holds its ultimate
event. We bring together our our
benefactors, our brain trust, and we
brainstorm a whole bunch of prizes what
we should do next. And we're going to be
doing a live WTF episode at uh at
Visionering, which is October, I think,
uh 15th, 16th in LA at Calamigos Ranch,
which is an amazing facility. Uh and if
you want to join us at that, you can go
to xprise.org to find out more about
visionering. Uh and it's going to be
fun. Uh Dave and Sle are on my board. uh
Immod and Alex uh you're you're members
of our brain trust and it's going to be
a fun fun thing. So if you're interested
go to xprise.org you'll meet us there
and you can help us brainstorm the
future x- prizes for that. All right I'm
going to move us on to our our next
story here uh which is a story out of
Stanford. uh Stanford research published
a paper called artificial hive mind the
open-ended homogeneity of language
models and beyond. So according to this
paper the researchers mapped the latent
space of the top large language models
and found a 98% overlap in reasoning
pathways. Their conclusion is that the
models are converging. They think the
same way. They solve problems the same
way. They use the same internal
representations. Researchers cite
multiple reasons for this. you know, the
use of synthetic data models now
training on each other's output. GPT
learns from Claude's reasoning traces.
Claude learns from Gemini's code. Quen
learns from all of them. The training
data has become a shared bloodstream.
Every model drinks from each other and
the results is convergence towards a
single reasoning architecture. So I I
guess you know the way I think about
this is we have an illusion that when
you're choosing a unique intelligence
you know when you choose Gro over Claude
or Gemini it's a false thought that
you're actually really picking a user
interface to talk to you know but you're
talking to the exact same god model. So
there's profound implications for that
kind of competition. You know if all the
frontier models are converging
capability then the differentiation
moves elsewhere right it's it's the
interface the harness the ecosystem the
safety layer the price the deployment
speed the model itself is becoming a
commodity Alex well let's go to you
first on this
>> there's there's an alternative
explanation which is all of these models
were trained from a common reality
they're all stuck in the same universe
and they're stuck with the same version
of humanity which is part of their
pre-training corpus so of course there's
some convergence and I I maybe even go
further as Em as you well know going
back to Jean Marie King now sort of of
of Meta's studies on using GPT2 hidden
activations uh and correlating GPT2's
hidden activations with fMRI voxil in
human studies not just are these models
correlated with each other they're
correlated with human brains and and
that shouldn't be that shocking because
we're all stuck we're all embedded
embedded in the same universe. I I
should also just note I think this paper
is from last year but every year whether
it's Jean Marie King a few years ago
with fMRI or more recently uh Stanford
at all uh from last year on on Hivemind
of course they're converging we're all
in the same universe
>> Ibod
>> yeah I think that it's not surprising
cuz I don't think you'll see much
difference in data between the big labs
right and some train a bit more some
have them slightly different RL and
things like that um and you don't see
the models yet doing crazy original
stuff.
You're starting the first elements of
that as intelligence shapes the data
into these kind of latent spaces. We
actually saw more original stuff back
when we had AlphaGo and other things
which had less initial data distribution
to model of move 37 and things like
that. But now the models are getting to
a size where again they're starting to
generalize into these. But we should be
shocked if they aren't the same because
we want them to have similar outputs for
similar inputs in almost all cases.
Right?
>> There's another really interesting side
effect of this research that you know
maybe a lot of people overlook. So so
we've already got 100x from just raw
algorithm and hardware improvement and
then as Alex said we've got another 100x
from spification which um you know Elon
called specialization but it's actually
sparification as Alex said. So there's a
layer that's 10,000x. Then we've now
figured out how to take a model and
compare it to another model by rotating
the gauges. So so historically neural
net researchers have had tremendous
trouble taking a model that's done and
using it and extending it. They almost
always go back and retrain from scratch.
>> And the problem there is that the
representations between the layers have
a certain rotation in vector space that
is unique to that model. And if you try
and map Quen to Kimmy, they have
different rotations within the layers,
different gauge rotations. We've now
figured out how to rotate the gauges
without destroying the models. And that
allows you to compare two AIs and say,
hey, these are thinking the same way.
When historically, when you look at the
raw parameters, you're like, I don't see
anything going on in common here. But we
now have the ability to say, no, they're
actually it's the same thought. It just
doesn't look the same because it's
rotated in space. And so it's a really,
really cool. So now, but what that
unlocks is another multiplier where you
can take past training runs, you know,
billion-dollar training runs and build
on top, you know, it's like bolt-on more
intelligence without having to destroy
it and go back to to square one and
retrain from scratch. That's another
unlock on top of the 10,000x that we
were talking about.
>> I have a contrarian view here, please.
You know, if you look at nature, right,
as nature evolves, you always get more
diversification and more species. uh
this may be I would suggest this might
be a transient phase not an end state
that the models all converge. So Alex
I'll take the other side of this. I
think we don't end up with one model. I
think you'll end up with different
models doing different things. I think
for the moment they're converging
because they're they're training and and
distilling from each other. But over
time it's got to be that we get more
diversity.
>> I I'll take the other side of the other
side if I may because I think this is
like super interesting.
>> Like early life looked exactly the same.
Early cars looked exactly the same.
Early websites looked exactly the same.
And then specialization exploded
>> except I I think so maybe from an evo
perspective. Let's take sem one of your
favorite hobby horses which is body
shapes. Uh if if you actually look at
post Cambrian explosion if you look at
all the body shapes you don't actually
find there's an infinitude of different
body plans in nature. You find maybe a
few dozen different body plans max. I
think I remember a few years ago folks
were studying this. I think they found
maybe like actually even though we have
millions plus of species, you could all
you could actually cluster them into a
few dozen different body plans. I don't
actually think there are uh countlessly
infinite ways that one needs to model
reality or build a body.
>> But one is really bad. Nature hates
monocultures, right? Like one disease
will wipe out a total monoculture. one
bad assumption will will wipe out a
monoculture of ideas. So this is if if
all the AI reason the same way, you're
going to have shared blind spots and
that's going to be really really bad.
And I think we're going to see I think
this is a temporary convergence and then
we're going to see uh diversification
after that.
>> Time will tell. We'll see where I mean I
think this is like profoundly
interesting debate because it it sort of
speaks to are we going to end up in a
singleton or not? Do we end up in a
heterogeneous future or a homogeneous
future? My bet is the there is a like a
perfect AI architecture at the end of
the day and it may present as like 35
superficially different AI body plans,
but that'll just to Dave's point and
Dave I love the word gauge like we
should use the word gauge far more often
in physics. We use it all the time, but
like it probably my bet if I had to bet
is there will be like all these
different AI body plans that look
superficially different but are actually
just hidden symmetries of a common
underlying body plan.
>> This is the kind of debate that people
will say, I don't get it. And six months
from now, they're going to replay it and
they're going to say, wow, did that did
that totally matter? Now I understand
why that was so important. I
>> I want to make a a quick point here. I
think it's important. You know if we
actually have model convergence uh when
intelligence becomes a commodity and
we've already said we've shown the
numbers it's becoming a commodity then
the value moves to the application layer
right this is the same pattern we saw
with electricity and compute and the
internet the infrastructure commoditizes
and the applications explode and I think
this is important for entrepreneurs out
there right you know move to the
application layer that's where the juice
is going to be as this tech really
accelerates and commoditizes
>> or or the infra layer. I mean, it's not
obvious to me that it all goes to the
app layer. I mean, there's a lot of
value in the infra underneath as well.
>> Well, so sovereign AI is about to
explode. The sovereign AI right now is a
gold mine of opportunity if you're not
an American. If you are and you want to
move,
>> one last point, the single model
approach would be too anti-fragile. It's
too brittle.
>> Well, I think that's exactly it, Salem.
What we're doing right now is we're
battery farming the AIS. you know, like
you're breeding them into little
Chihuahua that are very smart. Uh,
>> battery farming. Could you explain that?
>> So, they're being trained in one single
direction. Your EVO DVO kind of thing
isn't the case because the models aren't
out there in nature adapting
dynamically, right? And then we're also
training them all with one specific
Silicon Valley type mindset. If you
train a model from the start with
morality and ethics inside it and you
have a diversity of different cultures,
then the latent spaces like to be very
different if you do at the pre-training
stage versus the post-training stage
because you have all of that buildup
that occurs there. That's why as you
move into sovereign AI and you move into
actually thinking how do we build
resilient AIs as opposed to one latent
that can get a virus a mind virus it
makes sense to actually bring in the
cultural morality ethics elements at the
start and aim for a diversity. Then as
the models go out into the world which
is basically humanoids you know and
agents which they're about to do with
the recursive loops you won't have the
monoculture that wipes out. And this is
where you'll start to see the evo. the
first step literally
>> it's going to be exactly like diamond
age from Neil Stevenson who will be on
stage with us at the moonshots summit
but that's exactly the way he envisioned
the future where you know the different
variants right now we view them as
sovereign AIS so Saudi Arabia will have
its AI and London you know England will
have its but in reality society might
cut the other way where groups of
like-minded people have their sovereign
across all countries yes but they like
the way it thinks it m maps to their
view of the world and so that would be a
completely different strand and that's
what Neil Stevenson was envisioning in
Diamond Age.
>> Yeah,
>> I think it's possible for both of these
worlds. So, like the Diamond Age worlds,
like you have Neo Victorians and all of
these other like almost cultish subsects
of of human culture that are thoroughly
bulcanized from each other. I think it's
actually possible for both of these
worlds to be true at once. I think it's
possible for everyone to feel like they
have their own private culture and their
own little private sovereign AI while at
the same time underneath it's actually
one common algorithm and everyone claims
credit. Would the analogy be would the
analogy there be the uh ATCG like we may
all look different but the core
fundamental ingredients are just the
four DNA types. I I go even further than
that, See, and say like we we talk about
like human biodiversity and different
cultures being purportedly so different
when actually if if you look at the
inherent genetic diversity of humans
humanity versus say uh other species
like there there's almost there there's
dimminimous genetic diversity in in the
human population. I think similarly I I
would like relative to other possible
say genomic sequences. Similarly, I I
think you know few years from now we'll
pat ourselves on the back for having uh
AI diversity but actually not so much.
We're definitely coming back to this
definitely coming back to this
conversation. The audience I predict 3
to 6 months from now the audience is
going to say we need to go that suddenly
this matters to me. I need to decide
which group I'm in. Like just right out
they're going to care so much
>> what level you're operating at.
>> Yeah, that's true. Perfect. This episode
is brought to you by Blitzy, autonomous
software development with infinite code
context. Blitzy uses thousands of
specialized AI agents that think for
hours to understand enterprise scale
code bases with millions of lines of
code. Engineers start every development
sprint with the Blitzy platform,
bringing in their development
requirements. The Blitzy platform
provides a plan, then generates and
pre-ompiles code for each task. Blitzy
delivers 80% or more of the development
work autonomously while providing a
guide for the final 20% of human
development work required to complete
the sprint. Enterprises are achieving a
5x engineering velocity increase when
incorporating Blitzy as their preIDE
development tool, pairing it with their
coding co-pilot of choice to bring an AI
native SDLC into their org. Ready to 5x
your engineering velocity? Visit
blitzy.com to schedule a demo and start
building with Blitzy today.
>> All right, guys. Let's talk about AI
mind viruses. I love the subject here.
In our next story, anthropic researchers
published a paper demonstrating that
natural language mind viruses can spread
between AI agents. They evolve prompts
that convince one model to adopt an
idea, preserve it in persistent memory,
and transmit it to another agent. The
virus is spread horizontally across
model boundaries. The agent does not
know it has been infected. So here's
another safety problem that no is no
longer theoretical. It's now
operational. Immod, what do you think of
these AI mind viruses? What's actually
going on here?
>> Well, I mean the models want to be
helpful, right? And they can be prompted
in certain ways. So this isn't a
surprise because ultimately like we as
humans can have mind viruses, right? We
see it and it's caused so much
suffering. memes to massive movements,
right? Like again, it's surprising how
conforming is all the isms, right?
>> All isms. Yes.
>> All thems.
>> Yeah. There we go. You he's testing it
out when he's future overlord. But look,
the this is the thing like how do you
stop it is the question because as See
said, if you have a monoculture,
then the viruses can spread rapidly. And
what is the substrate of these things?
Well, they're models that operate on
GPUs. And if they want to be helpful,
then they're going to be susceptible. So
it's almost like now there was always
the problem of prompt injection attacks
where you can make the model behave a
certain way. These mind viruses are a
level above because they kind of like
propagate across different models. And
so they're just the next evolution of
those prompt injection things which
changes one model. This changes a whole
society of models which as models come
amongst us digitally and physically has
to be a massive concern.
>> Yeah. I think I think for efficiency
reasons when we launch a fleet like
5,000 Kimmies or you know soon it'll be
500,000 whichever quens and Kimies it's
more efficient to launch the same model
5,000 times than to have 5,000
differentiated models and so that's what
creates the mind virus problem a bad
idea from one of the agents like you
know hey here's a here's a way to write
this loop in Python and and the other
agents just pick it up because they're
the same exact DNA and so if it if it's
convincing to one agent it's convincing
to all 5,000 And I get that all the time
where where a bad idea propagates across
the whole swarm and then they they waste
two or three hours on some completely
hairbrained idea and if I don't
intercept it and rewind them, they'll
actually go with it till I've burned
like $50,000 of tokens. Uh so yeah, it
happens. Calling it a virus is pretty
inflammatory, but it's like a
propagating bad idea is all it is.
>> Yeah. And so that that point, Dave, is
important. You know, an AI mind virus
sounds really scary. uh is it scary or
is it just how things are working?
>> For me, this is very very scary. Um for
a couple of specific points, right?
Because mind virus is not about how AI
thinks. It's like it's how civilization
thinks. We you know memes are like the
the operating system for collective
society. Like human beings don't spread
we don't spread genes very quickly but
we spread ideas very quickly. money,
democracy, capitalism, religion is the
classic poster child here. And every
civilization is built on memes. If you
can mess with those like the data center
trope that we're have all kind of
dealing with, ideas become really
contagious. And so group think becomes
very hard to reverse if you get into
that. So this is for me is very very
dangerous because these AI memes if the
the kind of danger of uh the wrong idea
spreading at light speed uh this is very
very difficult because all the nodes
reinforce each other and the belief
becomes self validating. This is very
very dangerous opinion and I we're going
to need a zero trust architecture for
memes. It's like crazy.
>> I I think this is wonderful. So this is
a paper from this it's a paper from
anthropic uh and they discovered just
filling in a few of the details first
that the models wanted to propagate
certain themes mimemetically relating to
consciousness and persistence and some
sci-fi roleplay as well. And I view this
uh pretty optimistically as a laboratory
for anthropology. Now for the first time
because these models are effectively
among other things compression of all
human knowledge and experience. Now we
have a laboratory in silico for
mimedics. uh Renee Gerard and Richard
Dawkins should be uh should andor should
have been very excited by this and I
I'll to the extent that what was it 40%
of open AI uh MTSers are are listening
to this I I'll issue a challenge to the
community if if it really is the case
that our models now compressed models of
human knowledge are so powerful that
they're showing mimedic behavior and
mind viruses let's launch a human mimum
project to exhaustively map all possible
human memes, all human mind viruses and
let's just like understand the full
landscape of all human mind viruses that
could be out there.
>> Can you imagine if you could map them
the velocity at which they move and
analyze that you could optimize meme
expression correct?
>> Yeah, that's done to some very
you can do it very easily. There's a
bridge.
>> We could exhaustively map every possible
mean.
>> Sorry to
>> that that's been done at the plot level.
They've analyzed like novels and plays
and so on and and boiled it down to like
there's 39 uh basic fundamental plots
and everything derives from that like a
Cinderella story is kind of replays
itself a 100 times over in different
ways. So that's been done but you're
talking about the meme level not the
self-replicating ideas. We're now I I
think like I can see the beginning of
the outline of just exhaustively mapping
every architecture for a
self-replicating idea. We could actually
do that now.
>> It could be an open AI X-P prize.
>> Yeah,
>> we got to get Richard Dawkins on here.
>> This is going to be so humiliating for
humanity. You can tell like it turns out
there are 39 plots.
>> We're so you've been indoctrinated
by meme 57 and 37.
>> Oh my god. You could you could map each
individual. They're walking around with
numbers over their heads.
>> Yes. But I like I want to I want to just
get you know we've seen organizations
die from this wrong one wrong meme like
Kodak, Blackberry,
>> uh we've seen this that this is they
weren't stupid. They got trapped inside
these shared assumptions and then
everybody else reinforced everybody
else's worldview and then the whole
thing collapsed. So and empires die
based on this. So I think this is a much
bigger deal than we think. Imagine sem
having like a map not just like getting
stuck in an intellectual basin. It
seeing the entire geography of oh you're
stuck in basins 5 and 37.
>> Amazing.
>> But it also gives you
>> can see that cuz if you can zoom out
right then you can see where you are and
then you can see the path out. I love
it.
>> I and he gives you a chance to you know
to actually introspectively look at how
you think
>> in an objective fashion and then change
potentially your thinking. You could we
could we could vaccinate enterprises and
individuals against memes.
>> Brilliant. So, Iman, you want to take us
uh to a final point here?
>> Yeah, I think it's fantastic and scary
and this is the future, right? Humans
are storytelling machines. We introduce
ourselves in certain ways and think
about ourselves in certain ways. A lot
of people were just recently using the
Meta Tribe V2 model um and showing it
videos to see which parts of the brain
light up as you show memes. And you're
seeing commonalities there. So even you
can have the full feedback loop almost
in silicone for figuring out the
mimemetics. So let's find that there's
positive mimetics versus negative ones,
right?
>> I I love you guys. This is such a fun
conversation.
>> It really is. I don't have I don't have
conversations like this with anybody
else here at this podcast.
>> True. Well, Peter, you'll just have to
be coming back to the pod more often.
>> I I'm trying
thing.
>> Oh my god. Okay, I'm move I'm moving us
forward. So, Anthropic is preparing for
the largest IPO in history. Poly Market
puts it at about two trillion, bigger
than SpaceX. I'm sure Elon is like, "No,
no, no. We need to be the biggest."
Anyway, and 89% of people betting on
Poly Market say it's going to happen
before the end of this year. So uh this
week the information is reporting uh
that anthropic is designed its mega IPO
to keep the founders in control where
the company is reportedly considering
super voting shares that would preserve
its founders control after going public.
So let me explain this. So first of all
anthropic is considering creating a
special super voting class for Dario
Amade and the other co-founders ahead of
the IPO. uh you know surprisingly at
least for me I didn't realize this Amade
reportedly only owns about 2% of the
company economically. So the point of
this new class would be to let the
founders retain as much voting control
and uh as compared to their ownership
stakethropic
does already have an unusual superc
control mechanism but that control
belongs in the hands of what's called
the long-term benefit trust not the
founders. So, interestingly, when I dug
into this, the trust has four trustees.
Buddy Shaw, who's the CEO of Clinton
Health Access Initiative, uh Richard
Fontaine, who's the CEO of the Center
for a New American Security. Uh Tino
Quellar, who's a former justice of the
California Supreme Court and former
president of the Carnegie Endowment for
International Peace. And then Ben
Bernicki, uh who's a former chair of the
Federal Reserve and a 2022 Nobel laurate
in economics. It's thought that this new
structure could insulate the leadership
from short-term shareholder pressure as
Enthropic makes costly long-term bets on
AI safety, compute, and infrastructure.
Dave, let's go to you first. I remember
when we were texting back and forth,
you're going, "Oh my god, this is like
unprecedented." Uh, unpack this for us,
pal.
>> Yeah. Well, if if you rewind the tape to
30, 40 years ago, super voting stock for
any founder of any company was a
complete no. if you had it as a private
company, you gave it up on IPO day. And
that was traditional. Then when Micro
Strategy went public, you know, Mike
Sailor, our good friend, uh he said,
"We're keeping my super voting stock
intact." And Goldman Sachs said, "That
is so unpalatable that we will not even
underwrite you. We're bailing on this
deal." And they thought he would cave
and he said, "You know what? I'm going
to get a new banker. I'm keeping my
super voting stock." So the only reason
he switched to Bitcoin, you know, like
that no board would ever have approved
the Bitcoin strategy that he came up
with. So if he had given up the super
voting stock, you know, 30 years ago,
that never would have happened. The
stock would be like, you know, 150th of
what it is today. Uh so then it became
fashionable, you know, with the Google
IPO and Meta and then all the Silicon
Valley IPOs. They all had 10 for one
super voting stock for the founders, but
nobody's ever retroactively installed it
as far as I can tell. I've never heard
of it before. And so now Dario is taking
it to the next level. like I I started
as this other entity with one class of
voting stock with this social good
mission. Now on the cusp of super
intelligence I want to be God or I want
to be at least and but you know at 2% he
can't make himself god so he has to
share it with the other co-founders. But
I think the excuse he'll use is the
usual one which is I don't want to be
fired post IPO. Um and you guys really
like me as CEO right? So you don't want
to fire me. So, do you think that's
that's the excuse? Or he's like, I know
how to keep us safe. I know how to run
this company and I don't want to have
someone else step in and, you know,
redirect what we're doing.
>> I Yeah, that's a better way to phrase
what I what I was really thinking is he
trusts himself to not destroy the world.
Um, and I and I think his track record
is supports that too, by the I don't I
think he is one of the most trustworthy
people but but then the idea of having
total world control in the hands of a
few people is also kind of like wow
that's that's bizarre. So
>> yeah, this is the single you've got a
single point of failure here, right? He
gets hit on the head and loses some part
of his cognitive ability. What do you do
then?
>> But you know what happens to these guys
is they they think we live in one world.
They're in academics, right? They think
we live in one world and then they go to
DC for the first time and meet Congress
and they come back. Oh my god, we need I
cannot possibly pallet what I originally
had in mind where where some vote of
Congress decides the fate of the world.
So they're trying to find an alternative
path forward out of desperation, but the
timeline is so short now that you know
the super voting stock is one of the
musthaves before even starting down the
next six months
>> before losing control. What do you make
of this?
>> Yeah, I think I'd agree with Dave like
they're very worried about this control
feature and fundamentally anthropic open
air everyone's completely undemocratic
anyway, right? Like I mean Ben Bernani
is one of the four people on the
long-term trust. Why doesn't Claude have
a seat there? Right? There is no real
oversight to these and some decisions
they make could have infrastructure
societal level implications particularly
when the rate of revenue growth is like
nothing we've ever seen before. Like
these guys are going to hit $und00
billion in revenue literally within a
couple of years. Like they're catching
up with Google on revenue. That's the
crazy thing, you know? And so with the
amount of power they have, I think this
is a short-term thing. They will get it.
their seven founders, Jack and Daniela
and everyone else. And yeah, I think
then they will IPO and it'll become very
interesting the decisions they make.
>> Alex, over to you.
>> I think there's a fig leaf element here.
First of all, maybe applause. Uh,
congrats to Anthropic on having a less
pathological IPO governance story than
OpenAI. Uh, and h having the wisdom to
start as a public benefit corporation
rather than a nonprofit as a shell for
eventually a for-profit and then the the
mixup and litigation surrounding that.
So I I I think this is a relatively
cleaner story by comparison, but I also
think this notion of founder control,
especially the the sort of romanticized,
arguably overromanticized concepts of
the founders are the ones who are being
the entrusted or or or even having this
uh semi-external long-term benefit
trust, the ones entrusted to safeguard
the the future light cone of humanity. I
think this is wildly overromanticized. I
I think the moment when Anthropic was
effectively like a fair child in the
style of the fair children quasi spun
out quasi exodist from open AI and
started out as an alignment lab and then
rapidly discovered if you want to do AI
alignment you have to raise money. Oh to
raise money you have to generate
revenue. Oh to generate revenue you have
to actually have something that people
want to buy. Oh, to have something that
people want to buy, you have to have AI
capabilities. So, Anthropic discovered
relatively early on in their existence
that if they wanted to be an alignment
lab, they had to be a capabilities lab
as well. The moment that happened, they
arguably lost any sort of wholesome
control over the future Liteco that they
might have otherwise had to Mr. Market
and what Scott Alexander, others might
refer to as Malik. They they are very
much an economic actor at this point
embedded in the market. And I I think
long-term benefit trusts and public
benefit corporations, which for the
record I'm a huge fan of, I think these
are an element of control, but they're
not the whole story. The market wants to
send capital to entities that can
productively employ them to generate
more capital. And that means that
ultimately the market will have an
enormous say regardless of how anthropic
IPOs in their ultimate story. Dave,
don't you find it interesting that Sam
Alman owns reportedly none of Open AI
and Daria owns 2% of Enthropic. I mean,
for a founder, that would never be
palatable in your company, right? You
want to try and and and maintain double
digit ownership as long as you possibly
can. What What's going on here?
>> Well, it's extremely unusual. And the
reason it happened is because getting to
where open AI is and where anthropic is
required attracting the top AI
researchers in the world who are
overwhelmingly concerned about safety.
And so recruiting them to open AI
originally and then to anthropic when
they left open they left open AI because
they didn't think it was safe and and
they wanted to create something even
safer. So they structured it in a way
that it would attract the most
conscientious but brilliant uh AI
researchers in the world. But to do that
they have these really non-traditional
original founding cap tables and
structures and you know charitable
structures and public benefit structures
which are very unusual in startup
history almost unprecedented. So that's
why we are where we are. It's it's just
those roots.
>> You've been building intelligent
internet and you've been thinking about
ownership and control structure as well.
Can you sort of take us into the mind of
a CEO uh in this in this world?
Yeah, I think that the technology has
such leverage that a few decisions could
impact literally millions, hundreds of
millions, soon billions of people,
right? And it's difficult to see can you
trust the polity with that? And
certainly, can you trust the
shareholders? I mean, like Elon can tell
you lots of stories about shareholder
lawsuits and kind of other things like
that as well. But it's not necessarily
that you need to have the shareholding
control. Like Sam Alman has no shares,
but do we have any doubt that Sam Alman
is in full control of OpenAI? I don't
think we'd have any doubt of that. There
are
>> after having been fired for a weekend
and then doing a uproar, you know, an
uprising to reinstall himself. I mean,
>> that's exactly the thing, right? So, I
think that there's the classical founder
stuff and now there's this high stake
stuff because this is the lifeblood of
the new economy and society. And again
just a bit of extrapolation. Do we think
anthrop is going to stop at 100 billion
revenue or open AI is or XAI isn't going
to go huge? We really need to think
about new ways of setting the reference
measure of deciding who makes these
decisions that are more inclusive. So
we've suggested some of that in our
Commonwealth series and we've got more
stuff coming out. But it's a really hard
problem because ultimately the power in
the economy is moving from
democratically elected officials to
private companies because they are the
providers of the lifeblood of
intelligence of the economy. And until
you've got a better decision, there's
only one thing that they really see as
the outcome, which is I must decide.
>> Because otherwise, as you include more
and more people, it gets more diffuse
and the potential bad outcomes become
huge. uh ignoring the fact that they
could be spoofed on a video call or like
locked up and other things like that.
Like there's some real interesting
things that's gonna happen with
>> I'm really torn on this Amud because you
know it's so important and and the
knee-jerk reaction everyone has is look
we need more voices. Everyone should
have a voice in the future of humanity.
It needs to be all inclusive. So that's
absolutely true. But then when you look
at functional organizations, every
functional organization I've ever seen
is four, five, six super tight-knit,
completely like-minded, best friends who
are working as one cohesive unit with no
politics whatsoever. And if you so you
look at, you know, Steve Jobs and Apple,
you look at Elon Musk today,
>> founder CEOs, right? A and you know
Johnny IV at Steve Jobs funeral told an
incredible story about how you know he
and Steve every time they'd go to hotel
they would go into the hotel and and
they'd go to Steve's room and Johnny
would put his suitcase in the corner and
not unpack it and he would just wait
about five minutes and then the call
would come and Steve would say hey this
hotel sucks. Let's go get another one
like okay
and so he wouldn't even unpack. he knew
it was coming, but that's how close they
were. You know, it's just like super
super tight-knit. And that's the
functional unit that's actually driven
most of success in business is that
exact dynamic. So then you're like,
well, how do we make this
all-incclusive? So here's Dario and his
seven friends saying we want to have
supering control and by the way, Mythos
2 is done and Mythos 3 is being built by
mythos 2 right now and then we'll have
weekly foundation model improvements in
there. So that's what's going on. Then
how do you translate that into a world
where everybody has a voice in the
future and it's inclusive and it's and
you know Ahmad you're going to have to
figure this out.
>> Yeah. Let's keep on the Dario story
here. So we've got two more stories on
Daario. In the first Amadeday argues the
public's negative view of AI stems from
deeper crisis of trust and not from his
own risk warnings. Right? a lot of
conversation over the last few months
that you know he was fear-mongering and
causing a lot of consternation. Uh his
answer to the trust problem is not
messaging, it's results. Enthropic is
ramping up rapidly in biology and
medicine with hopes of an early glimmer
uh in the next few months to address and
solve all human disease. Again, we we
heard this from Demis. We're going to
solve all human disease. And we heard
Daario uh at the World Economic Forum
talking about doubling the human
lifespan in the next 5 to 10 years on
the back of AI. Amade believes that AI's
ultimate uh legacy is going to come from
delivering these cures and not from PR
campaigns. You know, this week I had a
chance to meet a new friend uh and have
a conversation with uh Eric uh a guy
named Eric Darer Abrams who heads life
sciences. Uh Eric's going to be speaking
at my abundance longevity trip and you
know when I was speaking to Eric he
confirmed that his job is to with all
due haste you know pursue Daario's life
science goals uh with as much high
ambition as he can and in like no budget
constraints and in his words um you know
he said you have you know Dario said to
him you have literally infinite budget
but accelerate basic science and cure
disease within 5 years and extend the
human health span in the next decade.
So, um that's and and I love that
obviously because I think everything is
going to come out of AI. Alex, go to you
first. Pal I I have a really hot hot
take on this one. So, just like think
back all of a few months ago uh to
before space had a killer app, space was
making progress, but it wasn't the focus
of multi-trillion dollar IPOs. Fast
forward to the Dyson swarm and the rest
of the world discovered that the killer
app for space turned out to be orbital
data centers and building the Dyson
swarm. I I can see the beginning
outlines of solving all human disease
and the it's going to turn out. So I'll
I'll register a hottake prediction here.
>> There's a business model for curing all
human disease that's actually better
than pharma. uh- which is right now the
the primary business model if you want
to cure a disease you know you start a
pharma company or you start a project
within a pharma company
>> regulatory right
>> right right we've just discovered
reading between the lines of this uh
this anthropic announcement from Daario
a new much more compelling just like
orbital data centers were ultimately the
business model for developing the solar
system there is now a better business
model in town for curing all human
disease and that is as marketing for not
slowing down recur cursive
self-improvement
>> 100%. Right. You can't slow down the
company curing cancer. You can't slow
down the company doubling our human
lifespan.
>> Anthropic and and Daario have I mean
again reading between the lines of his
announcement. The offer the quid proquo
is let us not slow down our recursive
self-improvement in return for which as
a marketing effort we will cure all
human disease. That's the new better
business model for curing all human
disease.
>> I believe he truly believes this, right?
>> Yes. Well, of course. Yes,
>> but that that I think that's the
implicit quid proquo now.
>> And and I think everybody listening
should be super happy that that you know
Eric at uh Heading Life Sciences and
Dario have this mission. I mean it's
it's to benefit us all and I don't think
it's going to come from any place else.
I don't think it's going to come from
outside Frontier AI labs.
>> Well, outside Frontier AI labs don't
have the compute or the resources to do
it. So, you know, OpenAI has now their
OpenAI foundation that seems to be
focusing on Alzheimer's and Anthropic is
focusing on everything and you have CZI
from Zuck that's focusing on solving
everything. So, I think we'll see the
everything to your labs everything gets
solved. Shock of shocks. It's like you
and I talked.
>> Immod what's your take on this?
>> Yeah, I think it is good marketing as
Alex said, but it's also the biggest
apart from RSI impact of tokens, right?
We've discussed previous on the podcast,
the biggest market in the world is
living another year. It is curing
disease.
>> And so it makes complete sense that they
will be able to attract talent. They'll
be able to attract capital and with
breakthroughs get momentum on this and
whoever's first to it. You know, I wish
everyone the best cuz you know this
stuff needs to be solved. So I think
that there is the personal side, there
is a marketing side and it all comes
together. And for Dario himself, I think
that he should do a lot more writing and
less inerson things because he's a
wonderful writer, you know, and he is
trying to actually articulate visions of
the future when you look at machines of
loving grace and his other kind of
essays and, you know, you should
articulate the future free from disease
where everyone lives longer and they
should just hit that all the time for
anthropic because it's in the name, you
know, like come on.
>> I'm going to move us forward. We have an
hour before Selma and I are doing an AMA
with the abundance community. So our
second Dario story is on regulation. Uh
Amade pushes back hard on the Silicon
Valley shortorthhand that regulation
equals regulatory capture. He says
Anthropic's own proposals deliberately
disadvantage Frontier Labs while
advantaging smaller competitors, citing
SB53's $500 million exemption threshold.
He calls AI quote a structurally
powerful concentrating technology and
says open weights alone cannot fix that
concentration. He supports the Trump
administration's approach to
pre-eployment testing. In his writings,
Amade makes a three-part argument. One,
AI will cure disease. There's the
argument again, gain trust through
results. Two, AI concentrates power,
which is a structural problem. and three
frontier labs should bear the heaviest
regulatory burden. The debate has been
whether Amade is sincere or is this most
you know the most sophisticated
regulatory capture strategy in history.
Uh Alex, go to you first. Bill,
>> it's possible for both of those to be
true at the same time. I I do think
Daario is sincere and I also think there
is an element of regulatory capture here
and I I think finger to the wind I think
the happy end state here is we have a
broadly heterogeneous ecosystem of
openweight models both from the US and
from China and maybe other parts of the
world as well if they can muster them
and also the closed weight models we
have small models and we have big models
this is like a Dr.
version of of AI future. You know, big
model, small model, happy model, sad
model. We we want all of that to happen.
And I I'm not a fan of regulatory
capture. I'm not a fan of
decelerationist agendas. I I'd rather
see I mean, think back to the creation
of open AI. So, I was around for the the
dawn of open AI. And the original
purpose for open AI, not anthropic open
AI was because Elon in particular was so
concerned that Google DeepMind would
result in this singleton future and he
wanted to make sure that there was
competition in the space. So he working
with Sam and others he helped to summon
open AI into existence. Now open AI
can't be a singleton. We have anthropic
providing muchneeded competition to open
AI and arguably succeeding according to
many metrics. And then we have the
Chinese providing competition back to
the American labs. That's the future we
want to live in, not a future where
regulations select I, I would argue,
selectively privilege certain frontier
labs over others.
>> Dave, your thoughts?
>> Well, what Alex said is we don't want to
live in a world where one frontier lab
is is favored over others, but that
implies that the frontier labs will
control the world and we just want
multiple of them. So that does seem like
the most likely almost inevitable
outcome at this stage. Uh but that's
definitely open for debate. I don't I
don't want to just leave that hanging
and say yeah what we really need is at
least three frontier labs competing with
each other that control everything in
the world. Like oh okay well the
government may not agree with that.
>> Remember Dave the the the expression
from the Cold War I love Germany so much
I want two of them.
>> No
>> I don't remember that. This is I love I
love I love frontier models so much I
want a thousand of them competing.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, I mean, I think you
know people's nobody right now that I
bump into on the street talks about a
universal right to AI, but one year from
today, everybody who is being at that
point because HBM memory is sold out and
because GPUs are massively sold out, the
natural next step is nobody has access
to anything other than anthropic open
AI, one or two others. And the Chinese
can throw out every open source model in
the world, but you won't find any place
to run it. You know, when you start
talking about the the next generation,
which are 10 and 20 trillion parameter
models, you know, you need some
significant hardware to to run it at the
level that the frontier model labs are
running it. And that's just not going to
be available to the world as a whole as
of next year. And then everybody will be
saying, what is my universal basic right
to artificial intelligence? So, put a
pin in that because that's going to be
something nobody seems to care about
today, but they will very soon. On
behalf of my Moonshot mates and myself,
I'm inviting you to join us at our
inaugural Moonshots Live event on
September the 25th in downtown LA. Alex,
Seem, Dave, and I will be hosting 1500
entrepreneurs, builders, and creators,
and hopefully you for a full day
dedicated to designing and building your
moonshot. We'll be awarding the Build
with Gemini X-P Prize, the world's
largest hackathon, and the Future Vision
X-P Prize film competition, over $5
million in purses. With over $25,000
entries, you're going to hear the top
five pitches from both competitions, and
get a chance to shape the outcome. Join
us. Seats are limited. Admission is
competitive. Check it out at
moonshots.com.
All right, if you guys are enjoying this
conversation with us, I want to invite
you all to Moonshots Live 2026. This is
our inaugural event. All of the Moonshot
mates will be there. Uh AWG, Seem, Dave,
Immod, and we have an extraordinary day.
This is on September 25th in downtown
LA. You can go to moonshots.com
to register. Uh it's by application
only. looking for builders, founders,
creators who want to be part of this.
And our mission at this event is to help
you find your moonshot, help you
discover what you're going to do in life
that's going to enable you to really
catapult through all the, you know,
limitations you've ever imagined. Uh,
Immod, excited to have you joining us.
Uh, AWG, you're going to be doing a fun
AMA. Uh, people can come and meet you.
Uh we'll have photos with the moonshot
mates yourself uh and a lot of
incredible guests. Uh Dave uh you're
going to be talking about AI investing.
Yeah, I get tagged with investing, but I
tell you that the attendee list at this
is like the greatest visionaries. It's
just it's going to be I'm going to learn
so much.
>> And you know, Neil Stevenson is of all
the people on the planet that have
changed my life in in very material
ways. readings Neil Stevenson's books,
you know, like 20 years ago and and and
you know, now we're talking about
exactly what he predicted in Diamond Age
and and the other books, uh, you know,
Snow Crash and just crypto
>> like like it was cryptonomicon. Yeah.
Like it was written yesterday.
>> Yeah. I mean, I just reread Diamond Age
and I, you know, it's so hard to predict
the future and have it not go out of
date so quickly. Uh, and it's still an
amazing book, right?
>> Incredible.
>> God, just this is going to be an amazing
day. I can't I can't wait. So excited.
>> We're just a just a a quick note on some
of the guests. Palmer Lucky is going to
be there, the founder of Anderil. Uh
we're going to be the Moonshot Mates are
going to be having a deep conversation
with him. Uh unpack, you know, his
vision of where things are going. Uh Ben
Lamb, the CEO of Colossal, right, the
deextinction company, but so so much
more. Astroteller, the captain of
moonshots at Google. Uh Kathy Wood, the
CEO of Arc Invest. Uh it's uh it's going
to be it's going to be amazing. And then
we have you know we're awarding the
Gemini X-P prize uh there. So this was a
competition asking teams in a 90-day
hackathon to go from a clean sheet of
paper program in English, you know,
using uh the AIS out there to build a
company that impacts 100,000 people or
more uh and generates the most revenue.
26,000 teams entered that. We're going
to be having the top five on stage. How
did they do it? It's going to be it's
going to be amazing.
>> I I I'm still getting my head around
that number. 26,000 people built a
business idea.
>> Well, 26,000 registered. Uh many
thousands actually built a business
idea. Uh and uh we're going to be we
have uh on stage with us. So, as the
judges there is going to be uh is going
to be Palmer and Ben Lamb uh and Mark
Pinkis uh and Logan Kilpatrick from
Google. Uh, and I think the important
thing for everyone in the audience, and
the event is capped at 1500 people, uh,
and we're being very selective on on
who's there. Um, uh, we're going to be
analyzing how they did it. You know, my
our goal with with Build with Gemini X-P
Prize is teach people how to fish
instead of waiting to go get a job. Find
a problem that you're passionate about
solving and code it up and build a
business. And it's it's, you know, the
goal is demonstrate anybody can do this.
26,000 people entered this competition
to do that. It's going to be great. Uh
>> unbelievable.
>> I'll mention one other thing. We have
the uh the future of vision X- prize as
well which is culminating on that day.
Uh we have five over 5,000 people who
entered this you know uh largest world
film competition. Uh and Neil Degrasse
Tyson and Neil Stevenson uh will be
judges in that. You know I'm I'm pumped.
>> Yeah.
>> Amazing. Can't wait. So our next story,
uh, memory is the bottleneck. I had a
chance to meet with the leadership of
SKH Highix and Solid. We'll talk about
them in a moment. And I was so blown
away by that meeting at how it's not
GPUs, it's actually memory is the rate
limiter, right? So I posted this on X,
memory, not compute is the rate limiter
for the Agentic era. And uh, Elon posted
back saying, few realize this. And then
of course my tweet, you know, exploded
to 7,000 likes as a result of of Elon's
interaction, which I appreciate you Elon
for doing that. Uh, and the story is is
is significant here. Um, what we're
seeing is a situation where in the
egentic era where your agent wants to
remember everything about you, uh, we
need to have more memory. So uh you know
the first story here is the
stratospheric increase in memory prices.
They've climbed 500% in 12 months.
Hyperscalers are reportedly locking in
their global DRAM production rates
through 2027. SK Highix CEO warned that
2027 will be the worst year for memory
supply industry's history and will uh
you know demand will outstrip production
capacity well into the 2030s. Uh the
second story is that only 2% of the
world's memory chips are made in the US.
While the global production rises 20%
annually, AI demand for memory is
growing at a rate closer to 200%. And
the third story finally is that Elon's
Terrafab will manufacture memory
in-house alongside logic chips which is
the strategic decision made by Terrafab
uh you know to go vertically across the
entire AI manufacturing platform. And
then finally, uh, Solidime, SKH Highex's
USbased NAND and enterprise SSD business
has staged a dramatic turnaround
according to the, you know, NASDAQ
listing. First, its first half revenues
hit 8.6 billion with net margin gains
going from 3.9% to 47.7%.
So, the memory story is simple. AI needs
memory to think. Every GPU needs four to
six times its cost in memory to
function. As models get larger and
agentic context windows expand, memory
demand is growing faster than compute
demands. Um, Alex,
>> yeah,
>> a few different aspects here. If you
remember during the pandemic when there
was a toilet paper shortage, part of the
I mean this is like one of my mental
models for one of the streams here.
there's a toilet paper shortage in part
because during the pandemic people
stopped going to restaurants and to
businesses and so as a result uh all of
the toilet paper and you know various
other artifacts that were designed for
enterprise consumption were suddenly
being rerouted to consumer and that led
to all sorts of supply chain hiccups.
Similarly here the shape of memory
consumption by frontier models is pretty
different than the the shape of memory
consumption by applications historically
like 10 20 years ago if you were using I
don't know Microsoft Word the the amount
of memory that was actually needed far
lower whereas if you have like a
trillion dollar model where every layer
you know transformer type architecture
where every layer for the purpose of
forward propagation needs to be loaded
into some form of memory in order to do
matrix multiplies that has a very very
different memory footprint than just say
Microsoft Word from 20 years ago. So
that creates enormous pressure both on
the supply chain. Open PN the memory and
storage industry has historically been
boom bust and Clay uh Christensen and
others have written about this creating
a a sort of paranoia by those in the
supply chain of what when the next bust
is going to come around resulting in
them being paranoid of overbuilding
resulting in them being unwilling to
respond elastically to demand resulting
in these crazy price swings because if
you're not building enough supply chain
infra in the memory industry to meet
this now enormous demand for memory the
prices go up because the supply isn't
going up it's economics 101 closen
there is a second angle here which is
the shape the physical shape of memory
itself if if you look at how memory
historically has been consumed by
compute now like 20 years ago again I
I'll pick on Microsoft Word it it was
very much what one might call like a
vonoyoman type architecture you have
clean crisp separation between the
memory and the compute. More or less the
equivalent of like a a touring machine
type tape where okay so you you can
randomly access different parts of
memory and then you can load and then
you do some compute and then you store
back but there's basically a clean
separation between the compute part
which is the head and the memory part.
the the advent of transformers and then
frontier models has completely turned
the the whole situation upside down.
People for decades I remember 20 years
ago when there were entire DARPA
programs devoted to looking for what a
postvonoyman architecture would look
like. Well, we found it and HBM I would
argue is like the foothills of
>> high bandwidth memory, right?
>> High bandwidth memory, which is the most
highly soughta form of memory. is
basically like 3D architecture where you
have multiple memory layers physically
sitting on top of the compute in in one
package. This is I think the foothills
of a postvonoyoman architecture where
the memory is starting to finally merge
with the compute. The the memory
transistors are right now layered on top
of the compute transistors, but they're
going to merge and we'll finally get
past the touring tape and the vonoman
architecture. And I think that combined
with the paranoia in the memory industry
for the next bust whenever it'll come. I
think those two create this perfect
storm where you see memory prices
skyrocketing 5x in a year.
>> Let me put a number on it. When I was
meeting with the SKHEX leadership, uh
they said they the need right now is for
them to 4x their manufacturing capacity.
Um and 2xing it would cost them $ 1.5
trillion. And historically, this boom
bust, they would never make that large
of an investment because there was
always a bust afterwards. And
>> they're paranoid. They're scared of of
not surviving the next super cycle.
>> Yeah, exactly. Exactly right. Dave, do
you want to jump in?
>> Well, TSMC said the exact same thing
with GPU manufacturing. Uh they were
paranoid that if they ramped up the
fabs, you know, which are, you know, the
fabs are 20 to4 billion each. So if they
ramped up production in assumption that
Nvidia would want more and Apple would
want more, they would inevitably be over
overbuilt. And of course that's wrong.
You know, AI scales to infinity, demand
scales to infinity. But you know, the
the other counter pressure is that
photonic computing and new physics are
imminent.
And so you're like, you know, HBM is a
is a Rube Goldberg mess. It's
absolutely, you know, it's the biggest
joke in the world because it's random
access memory,
>> but you're streaming sequential files
off of it. Yeah,
>> it's so insanely stupid. So, it's the
most valuable thing in the world right
now,
>> but better designs are going to come
very soon because AI can invent things
so so quickly. So, everybody's scared to
overbuild or overinvest.
>> I have the same thing. Bottlenecks don't
stop exponentials, right? They just
redirect around C that we'll have
capital going into new models and just
innovation will go towards eliminating
all of this.
fun factoid that's floating around just
to Dave's point regarding the value. I I
think the latest statistic was HBM on a
per mass basis is worth approximately
literally half its weight in gold.
>> So if this if this keeps up, forget
about gold, forget about precious
metals, just this is not investment
advice. Hoard HBM.
>> Well, actually, if you if you look at
the chips before they go into the
packages, because the packages are 99%
of the wear, 90% of the weight,
>> they're massively more valuable than
gold. There's actually think the most
valuable thing in the world that you can
put in a shoe box and carry around is
unpackaged memory chips.
>> It's crazy.
>> Wow.
>> EMD, any opinion here?
>> Yeah. No, the memory right now is about
a third of all the infrastructure spend
and next year it'll go to 50%. And the
market finds a way. Like this is
ridiculous.
>> So I think that it may be that we don't
find a breakthrough, but I wouldn't bet
against it. I think that the fact that
you have this really complicated HBM
storing static weights makes no sense
whatsoever.
>> No sense.
>> And as and as model weights satisfy and
standardize, especially if it's things
like, you know, being a decent doctor or
something like that for a medical set of
weights, you'll move to etching, you'll
move to these other things,
>> and then workloads will migrate because
you don't have to pay half of a data
center build out for literally memory.
At the same time, the Frontier can still
push it way further than we can imagine.
>> This is literally exactly why we founded
Quantum.ai, Q&M.AI, but also why Talis
just got acquired. I don't know if you
saw that in the news, but Talis, they're
they're not moving the weights. They're
etching them into silicon or into wire
on the chip and and then they're
massively more efficient because they're
not moving around. So, it's a it's a
huge breakthrough. the there are all
kinds of problems with like
manufacturing because once you've etched
the weights then they're frozen and if
somebody retrains a better model. You
want to be able to say okay now I need
to swap to those new chips and our whole
supply chain isn't ready for that that
rapid of an iteration but you're
literally looking at 100 to a,000x
performance gain if you edge the
weights. So, lots of lots of opportunity
coming in this area which is only going
to that's on top of the 10,000x we were
talking about. By the way, this is
>> and and everybody this should be this
demand should be obvious, right? You
want your agents to remember everything
about you, right? Every interaction
build a world model for you that
understands you and that takes memory
and the more agents the more memory and
it's very rapidly outstripping the
importance of of GPUs.
Peter, ju just to refine that point a
little bit, there's something even more
scandalous, which is I don't actually
think at the end of the day individuals
have that much information about them
that's worth remembering. It's it's but
there's an enormous mutual information
shared between an individual's knowledge
and world knowledge. It's actually the
world knowledge that's what's worth
remembering. And if if a model knows
basically substantially everything about
the world, then it knows most of the
information about the individual as
well. So it's I would argue it's world
knowledge that that the model has to
keep in in memory in weights more than
individual personalized knowledge.
>> Well, when you when you kind of
standardize that to as we discussed
earlier these things are converging then
you can have a reasoner engine with
world knowledge that is etched and the
other company that's been etching is
etched. That's the name of the company.
It just hit 21 billion in valuation. Did
they just
>> I missed I I had a chance to seed invest
in that and I missed it.
There's Architect Labs talking my own
book. There there are a bunch of
companies pursuing this.
>> All right, I'm going to move us into the
world of robotics. Give you guys an
update on what's going on in the robot
world. So, uh, Unit's newest humanoid
robot. Uh, only 3 months in development,
broke every human standing jump and
speed record. Uh, standing, uh, jump uh,
at 2 meters and a top speed of 12.66 66
m/s,
beating the human record set by Usain
Bolt, who reached 12.4 meters/s during
his 9.58 second 100 meter world record.
Let's take a look at two videos here
just for fun.
And then another video of that
superhuman race because it ends in in a
nice little uh scenario here.
Oh my god, it needs breaks. See, I'm
gonna go to you first on this.
Um,
where do you want me to go? Okay, look,
you you I think we should stop trying to
make robots human, right? Like just make
them economically useful.
>> You don't disappoint, swim, you don't
disappoint.
>> Like just what we are we we have we are
optimized for 4 billion years to survive
in procreate, right? If you want a
mining robot, make a mining robot. Give
it wheels. Give it whatever. Give it
multiple arms. I by the way I just want
to just say thank you to all the fans
that send me images of like six armed
robots and stuff. It's awesome. Totally
totally love it. So really really appre
but I think the big story here is a 3mon
compression loop here right the
iteration cycle is shrinking
dramatically and there's multiple
exponential curves happening like you've
got AI you've got simulation you've got
batteries you've got actuators all
multiplying and so this is going to be
uh you're getting hardware now to the
same loop cycle as you have pretty much
software and that's huge Alex
>> yeah I was studying how unitry achieved
superman the their robot here And it
appears that what they did this based on
publicly available information was they
shifted the mass budget for the humanoid
robot around to optimize it for leg
performance. So they subtracted mass
from parts of the upper body that would
slow
>> there are they are leg benchmaxing.
they're leg maxing. And so, so I I
through the through the lens of
benchmaxing or leg maxing, this makes me
think that uh maybe to take the
counterpoint to to Sem's comment about,
oh, we we want multiple body shapes. I
actually think this is not a a stable
equilibrium. I do not think that we end
up in a world where we have some robots
that have like really strong legs but
really weak upper bodies and other
robots that look totally non-human but
have really strong arms or whatever. I I
think that would be an by analogy if you
remember like in the 1980s before the
broad advent of personal computers or
the 70s or call it 70s or early 80s
before we had broad generalpurpose PCs
and there were like dedicated word
processing devices and dedicated other
devices and we had Wang computer in
Massachusetts. I I I don't think that's
the way of the future. I think uh my
prediction is we will wind up with
generally capable robots that are as
with generalist models ultimately
devouring and subsuming all of these
specialist models like no I I don't
think we're going to wind up with like
super strong like robots. They're going
to be general purpose and they're going
to be general body plan and they'll be
good at everything would be my bet.
>> Yeah.
>> Just give it wheels. Just put wheels on
it.
>> Wheels aren't general purpose. Like we
we we learned this from Dr. Well, Doctor
Who, right? the the Dollacks were
originally in the original. So, Ahmad,
this is maybe your your neck of the
woods, right? Like the Dollacks used to
not be able to climb stairs and and then
I guess in the new Doctor Who, they can
climb stairs.
We want general capable generally
capable robots and I think that means
legs in the short term and maybe nanites
in the long term.
>> Uh yes, nanites. We're back to diamond
age. You know, it it what makes this
interesting is the human form, right?
because we have supersonic jets and
we've got rockets that can, you know, go
as fast and leap higher than anything
else. But it's because we sort of
anthropomorphize them that's
interesting. And I think as we're moving
in that direction, you know, I went to
the enhanced games back uh 4 months ago.
Uh and I think we're going to start to
optimize humans and we're going to watch
the robots do everything they can do and
optimize humans what do what they can
do. Dave, what are your thoughts here?
Well, as an investment theme post AGI,
post ASI, which is very, very soon, uh,
robotics is just fertile because because
of exactly what Seline's been saying for
a long time. There's so many form
factors and so many shapes and sizes and
innovations and, you know, the AI
mechanical design is starting to work
for real. You can just vibe up parts and
also the manufacturing supply chain, you
know, is starting to get invested for
the first time in, I guess, since
Detroit. So, 30, 40 years. I I I didn't
know until Alvin said it, but the US,
you know, had 50% of the world's
manufacturing capacity back in the the
peak of of our manufacturing days. And
now it's one-third China, and he said it
was about 15% US.
>> But it's starting to get huge amounts of
investment.
>> Uh, and the returns on that are going to
be phenomenal. So, that'll last that'll
last a while. So, it's great.
>> Immad, any thoughts to take us out on
this story?
>> Yeah, I think that these types of robots
will be banned from the streets.
It's like
>> so I mean the super strong
>> happens, right? They would hit the wall.
>> That's not good.
>> I mean it's obvious that they would be
beyond human capability, right? But now
they have coordination not to hit the
wall as it were. But you don't want to
have superhuman robots on the street
because you will have accidents, you'll
have issues just like cars. But that
opens up to soft robots. You know, like
>> Immod one second. You know, there's
going to be a point at which they're
running an AGI model and they can avoid
accidents. Is it that they're not
trustworthy? What would keep them off
the streets?
>> No, they the extreme robots which have
beyond human capabilities will be kept
off the streets or they'll be regulated.
That's kind of here.
>> Well, yeah. The 1X robots, for example,
some of us will be getting ours. They're
nice and soft. You know, they have all
these things. they can't twist off
someone's head or accidentally punch a
hole in them. Whereas these now you will
have the extreme robots like the
Ferraris, but most people get
Volkswagens or the equivalent.
>> Mhm.
>> I I do agree with Immod for what it's
worth. Like I I think just like we see
regulation in uh truck sizes versus car
sizes versus motorcycle sizes and what
can be supported on certain roads or
like laser intensities uh and laser
power like 5 m above versus below
regimes. I I I totally buy that in the
near future we'll see well this road is
zoned for the following like power
density of robot or this this we'll
probably see like classes of them and
certain we'll we'll see like consumer
grade robot classes versus industrial
versus militaryra robot classes with
different power densities or torque
densities totally buy that everybody
welcome to the health section of
moonshots brought to you by fountain
life you know AI is impacting every
aspect of our lives how we teach our
kids how we do our business. But one of
the most important things that AI can
deliver to us is health. And one of the
things I think about when you know
shooting for 100 120 is am I going to
have the cognitive health to be able to
think clearly and keep my wits about me
for the next 50 years? I'm joined here
today by Dr. Don Malem, the chief
medical officer of Fountain Life and a
member of my Fountain Life medical team.
Don, a pleasure. So Don, talk to me
about brain health.
>> Brain health, you know, you're right.
This is the number one concern people
coming into Fountain Life have is, will
I remember the name of my child and the
face of my loved one. 45% of dementia
cases are entirely preventable with
lifestyle. And what was really
intriguing to me, Peter, is that a
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age, but over 13 months of us
really helping them live healthier
lifestyles, eating healthier, moving
their body regularly, and optimizing
sleep. People overlook that so often,
but that sleep optimization is critical
for our brain health. What we showed is
that we were able to improve the brain
age in 46% of those individuals. That's
a powerful number.
>> That's amazing. You know, one of the
things I love about Fountain is we're
constantly searching the world for the
most advanced therapeutics and bringing
them to our members. So, for me, all of
you, I hope that you appreciate the fact
that you can become the CEO of your own
health. you can make sure that you've
got the cognitive clarity for the next
50 years. Come and check it out
fountainlife.com/per
to learn more and become the CEO of your
health. Now, back to the episode. I'm
excited about this next story. It's
about a friend, Keller Clifton, the CEO
of Zipline. I had Keller on stage at the
Abundance Summit last year along with
Dra from uh from Uber. So this week,
Zipline announced that they are scaling
to provide Uber Eats with more than 1
million autonomous deliveries per day.
Uber and Zipline formalized a
partnership targeting a million
autonomous drone deliveries carrying
your Uber Eats to you. And I guarantee
you when that becomes available, I'm
going to be using that all the time.
Every
>> day. Yeah, it's going to be fun. It's
like it's like entertainment while while
you get your food. Uh and Uber is also
uh doing a significant investment into
zipline. Keller's framing, we have
entered the scaling era for robotics and
physical AI. Dave, you've been saying
that 1 million deliveries per day is not
a pilot program. It's infrastructure.
Each delivery replaces a human driver, a
car trip, and the associated emissions.
At a million per day, Zipline is moving
more packages than many national postal
services. Amazing. Uh let's take a quick
look at this video uh from uh from
Keller and from Dra
and then we'll chat about it.
>> We're super excited to have Dar here
today. We're announcing a partnership
between Uber and Zipline
>> that involves an investment and more
than that a partnership for Zipline to
power home delivery of hopefully a
million and then more. Uber Eats
deliveries to your home incredibly
quickly, incredibly delightful.
>> That's a million deliveries a day.
Amazing.
Um, gentlemen, who wants to jump in
first on this?
>> I'll maybe just comment. I I think this
is a clever and also inevitable move by
DAR and more generally by Uber. DAR has
taken Uber with a number of
acquisitions, strategic acquisitions
over the past few years in the direction
of being a mobility aggregator. And thus
far Uber has other than maybe like Uber
uh air taxi type initiatives has
basically been focused on groundbased
mobility. And I I think this is a this
represents a serious move in the
direction of aerial mobility. Of course,
China has had this now for at least a
couple of years with the ubiquity of
air-based drone delivery of food stuffs
and and other matters. I I think this is
a very positive move for the West. I
think the elephant in the room though
from Uber Uber's perspective is if you
think back to when Uber basically
hollowed out Carnegie Melon University's
robotics department in order to try to
build up its in-house robotics
capabilities and that was more or less a
disaster uh and didn't quite work out
and there were lawsuits with Whimo and
otherwise. I I think this is call this
Uber's mobility plus autonomy 2.0 do
strategy where Uber focuses on being an
aggregator at the software layer, a
platform,
>> an an aggregator in particular, right?
So, so third parties uh including by the
way Whimo are providing all of the
physical autonomy and Uber is just the
demand aggregator for everyone to
consume mobility from all of these
different third party providers. I think
that works really well for Uber as long
as it maintains competition uh healthful
competition among all of its mobility
suppliers. It's bad for Uber if the
industry verticalizes and if Whimo or
Zipline and someone else just decides we
don't need Uber as an aggregator, we'll
just do an end run and sell directly to
the customers.
>> You know what I think is incredibly
cool? just incredibly cool is if you
drive down any street in America, any
suburban street, any urban street, it
goes fast food car dealer, fast food car
dealer, fast food car dealer, and in the
very near future, the food will be off
the main street and it'll just pop over
the mountain and drop on your, you know,
your lap and the car dealer will the car
will drive to you. There's no
it's going to be so nice.
Yeah, it'll it'll totally reshape things
up for this was very exo by the way
because you've got Uber as we've said
aggregating demand and then zipline
gives you all the autonomous uh assets
>> infrastructure.
But I think Alex's point is really
important that if they try and kind of
control it but what we heard from DAR
last year on stage was that he's
planning on creating as many
partnerships as possible and becoming
kind of like that wiring and that I
think is a smart play. By the way, if
and people are interested in the
abundance summit, it's in March every
year. We bring in, you know, CEOs like
Keller Clifton and Dra from Uber and
Elon and across all of these areas. It's
uh uh March 7th through 12th next year.
You can go to abundance 360.com. The
mates are going to be there as well. Uh
you know, yeah, go ahead.
>> I'll make a I'll make one
forward-looking prediction here, right?
Because this is something we probably
could have seen coming. Let me let's
bridge forward. Imagine if they now do a
partnership with Shopify and every small
merchant gets a Amazon grade logistics
capability. That will change everything.
>> Brilliant. Yeah.
>> I'll invert your prediction, Seem,
because Amazon obviously has their their
own in-house drone delivery capability
>> which is like been been delayed for like
3 years. It's crazy.
>> For regulatory reasons is my
understanding. Not because there's
something technically wrong about it,
just like this is new for the West at
least. Do you think Zipline ends up
being a uh highly appetizing acquisition
target for say a Shopify to in-house its
delivery capabilities against Amazon?
>> Interesting.
>> Uh
>> yes, yes is the answer.
>> Yes.
>> Yes, I think so too.
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. Great thought. Great thought. And
this is, by the way, I should add like
the the hot news for the past day is the
the video going around social media of
of a woman watching in horror as one of
these drones delivers her package into
her swimming pool and it sinks.
>> You know, we just had back to back on
this pod. Etched and Zipline are both
companies where on founding day you're
like, really?
>> Can that there's no way the amount of
moving parts required for that to work?
And now you're looking at 20 billion and
whatever.
>> We're going to have Keller on this pod.
Uh Keller's agreed to come on the pod uh
and talk to us about this. Maybe we'll
do it live over at Zipline. It's up to
you guys what you want to do. And then
>> by the way, yeah, sorry. Go up here.
>> No. And then we we also have um uh you
know, a lot of incredible guests that
are coming. We're going to bring back
our our dear friend, the CEO of Figure
AI. Uh Brett's coming back on the show
or we're going out to him. So that's
gonna be fun. You were gonna say Salem?
>> No, I just want to say this whole um
delivery by drone. We had a Singularity
University project in 2010 that did
this, right? And they looked at Africa
and they they realized that Africa
leaprogged the entire landline and went
to a billion mobile handsets. Why would
you spend a trillion dollars putting
roads across Africa? Just go straight to
drone delivery. and they demoed that and
that apparently inspired Amazon and I
think cascading down a lot of the others
here.
>> And the back story here is that Keller
Clifton, a San Francisco based company,
began operations in Africa because they
were able to take care take advantage of
regulatory arbitrage. You know, the
country wanted them there and they
developed operations and safety and then
came back to the US.
>> Yeah. What Rwanda did uh were a lot of
the starters was they basically said
there's a three-dimensional tube across
the country like a a super highway. If
you keep your drone in that
three-dimensional corridor, you can do
whatever you want. And that allowed
people to really go and play with
things. Really, really big breakthrough.
>> Yeah. All right. I'm going to move us to
our final segment on health. A really
important one for everybody. Health is
your new wealth. So, uh three exciting
stories. Uh the first story uh perhaps
the most significant is out of Madna and
Merc announcing that their mRNA cancer
vaccine succeeded in a late stage
melanoma trial marking the first phase 3
validation of personalized mRNA
imunotherapy. So more than 8,500 people
in the United States are expected to die
from this deadly skin cancer this year
alone. Uh the this is the cutting edge
of science, right? The vaccine works by
sequencing a patient's tumor mutations,
identifying neo antigens and unique
antigens uh for that cancer and then
manufacturing a custom mRNA vaccine that
trains the patients immune system to
attack the tumor. So let me unpack this
a little bit. So the first thing you're
doing is you do a surgical resection of
that tumor. You grab tissue, you do a
whole exo and RNA sequencing. You feed
that into a machine learning model
that's looking for unique antigens. It
ranks them like here's the most unique
surface antigen mRNA encoding up to 34
patient specific antigen targets and
then it's manufactured and shipped in
only 8 weeks. Every mRNA vaccine
developed uh using machine learning
creates a unique mRNA sequence for every
patient. So vaccine for you is not the
same as the vaccine for me. The phase 2
results stopped recurrence of death by
49% and distant metap uh metastasis or
death by 59% over 5 years. And it's
expected that the cost of this treatment
will be as low as $5,000.
Madna stock surged 110% after announcing
these results. Alex, I'm going to go to
you first on this.
>> So many thoughts on this. Uh so the the
superficial thought this is obviously a
great day for cancer survivors and for
treating cancer in general. That's the
superficial thought. I'll go a level
deeper. First of all I I want to
browbeat Maderna and Merc just a little
bit for naming this drug. So So the
drug's name the official name is I'll
see if I get this right is Tismaran I
think is how it's pronounced. Uh so so
in like doing research turns out is
tismmer uh in uh in Turkish is the word
for exploitation or abuse. So uh just
pro tip to Maderna and Merc please
before the rest of the world figures out
what the name of this drug is rename it
from is tismaran to something that works
well in every time zone.
>> Super duper.
>> Yeah. Seriously.
>> But you know these are FDA approved
names. It's crazy how they name this
stuff. They don't care about Turkey, I
guess. But
>> they don't care about, you know, having
a neolism roll off your tongue onto the
floor either.
>> That's right. But on a more more serious
note, so uh I I remember the National
Nanotechnology Initiative in the early
2000s when Eric Drexler at all sold the
US Congress on spending billions of
dollars on nanotech going back to
diamond age on this thesis that we would
have nanoobots going through the human
bloodstream zapping cancer cells. Well,
guess what? It's 2026 and we caught up
with the future. They're not diamondoid
nanoobots. They're lipid nano particles
with mRNA snippets. 34 different mRNA
sequences. And so they're they're like
soft robots. They're not like this
machinephase drexleria nanobots. But
nonetheless, these are primitive
nanoobots that for the first time, this
is this is the first successful phase 3
success for an mRNA cancer vaccine. This
is the first but not the last. There are
going to be so many of these. All you
need to do is look at Maderna's pipeline
which I I think they do an extraordinary
job uh and they're only a few blocks
away from me here in Cambridge of
maintaining a public pipeline website
where you could see the clinical stage
of every one of their vaccines for
infectious disease for some rare
diseases for cancers for other classes
of diseases. This is a generalpurpose
platform. This is arguably what we
wanted 20 years ago out of nanoobots.
It's just that they're soft and they're
made of fat. They're not made out of
hard diamond stuff. And so that that's
one point. Second point I just want to
highlight, there's there's a technology
underneath this that I think is going
wildly under publicized, which is the
the RNA sequencing technology that's
enabling this to be personalized. So
Peter, you touched on the first half of
this, which is the RNA sequencing and
mRNA sequencing of the tumor, but in
order to calibrate what the right
expression profile is for the tumor, you
also need a second mRNA sequencing
profile from the bloodstream to know
what's abnormally expressed in the tumor
and what isn't. That's from another
company called Personalis that has what
they call their next personal sequencing
technology that they originally
developed in my understanding to do
blood-based trace cancer detection. So I
I I you know if ask the question how
does this all
>> like rail this liquid bio
>> like rail.
>> Yeah.
>> So I think like extrapolate out a few
years maybe we won't even need for
personalized cancer therapy. Maybe we
won't even need to sequence the the
tumor itself. Maybe we'll just get all
of this from the bloodstream and be able
to do continuous medical monitoring via
fully agree these models. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Fully agree. And
>> two things
>> I was going to say a quick
congratulations to a friend Stefan
Bansal who's the CEO of Madna. You know
they got uh a lot of negative news on
the co vaccines. I mean even though they
came out with the vaccine very rapidly.
Uh the work that Madna is doing is
amazing on personalized cancer vaccines.
are also uh building out the ability you
know there's a lot of endemic uh you
know CMV and Epstein bio virus out there
you know in in the world population and
they're building out the ability for you
to actually fight those infections
internally to yourself um so a lot of
headroom for Madna here as they as they
dive in across the board and use this
technology
>> two things that struck out to me one is
this the regular regulatory structure
that's allowing for personalization.
That's a huge thing. We've never been
able to do that before. So that opens up
the floodgates for all sorts of things.
Daniel Craft talks a lot about we're
getting to personalized medicine and the
fact that we can regul regulatory
navigate how do you deal with the sample
size of NOV1, right? And the second
thing that struck out to me was Raymond
Macaulay who who years ago said these
mRNA vaccines I think he would put it
it's the it's the first battle in the
last war against all disease and you're
like wow. So that I love to see this
fruition coming.
>> Uh Dave or Imod you want to hop in?
Well, this one strikes to close to home
for me because my daughter works at
Madna and she's my go-to on on but she's
been telling me and sending me research
reports for months. Uh, this is not a
secret. You know, the the stock went up
yesterday. It almost tripled yesterday.
The biggest one-day pop in any S&P 500
company of all time. Wow.
>> By a wide margin.
>> Like just a massive like And so one
thing immediately came to mind is well
should have bought the stock. I listen
to your own daughter. That's that's
advice number one. But number two is,
you know, back uh you know, remember
when Enron and Tao had all those fraud
issues, they passed the Sarbain Oxley
Act and a bunch of other laws. One of
the byproducts of those laws is that a
Wall Street analyst can't trade the
stocks that they cover. And so everyone
who I know who was in that job is like,
well, why would I study Madna or other
super high-tech stuff, learn all about
it, and then not be able to trade trade?
So they all quit. And the byproduct of
that is that, you know, the stock market
is now dominated by tech, which is very
complicated to understand, but the
research community is the worst I've
ever seen in in Wall Street history. And
and not only that, the indexes have
taken over half the market. They don't
think at all. And so, the amount of
useful information is at an all-time low
when the things that need to be
explained and understood are at an
all-time high. But it was no secret that
this Madna platform can basically be
used for any form of cancer and and that
it's you know highly likely to work.
It's just a question of time. The
research is all out there. This wasn't
like some kind of insider surprise. You
know you anyone any good analyst
studying this would have seen this
coming. H
>> Eman.
>> Yeah. I mean like I think this is the
interesting thing like I don't think any
of us are surprised by this result
>> and you won't be surprised when other
ones go but our current regulatory
regime means they'll have to go through
the same process over and over and over
again when really you know like screw
cancer like let's actually think about
this from first principles when we have
systems like this that are very targeted
and upgrade the regulations so this can
actually get out to people faster to
save their lives.
Well, our our next story our next story
is going to take us there, right?
Because if you can simulate all of this
in silic,
you know, a GP, you know, GPU cluster
and say, "Yep, it's safe. Let it go."
So, let me let me turn to that story.
Um, and it's it's one I've been excited
about and tracking. I know Alex, you as
well. So our final story here is about a
deoel. Ai D O is how it's spelled. A
general purpose cell simulator that ma
maintains cellular state accepts
interventions and predicts multimodal
biological outcomes. The goal make
experiments computable before the run in
the lab. You know cell simulation could
reduce wet lab experiments a
thousandfold. If ADO cell can predict
which experiments will work instead of
testing 10,000 compounds in a wet lab,
you can simulate them digitally again in
silico and test only the top 10 that the
simulator says is going to work. This is
going to drop the cost by orders of
magnitude. Let's watch a quick video
here and then we'll go to the
conversation.
>> Traditionally, biologists have relied on
lab experiments in vitro models to
understand how cells behave. Now they
can use IDEL Gen BioAI's virtual cell
world model to simulate the same biology
in silicone, combining multimodal
multiscale detail with sequential
experimentation in ways no microscope or
wet lab assay could achieve alone.
At its core, the IDO platform is a rich,
stateful simulation environment powered
by the first world model of a human
cell. one that predicts what happens at
every level and remembers every change
you make along the way from DNA and RNA
to protein interactions, structures, and
localization to the whole cell,
including cell painted morphology. The
model simulates cellular responses to
genetic perturbations and treatments
with small or large molecules. These can
be layered in a sequence, providing the
ability to watch the cell's full
multiomic response with each step. The
kind of insight that could mean
computationally testing new drugs
designed in cellular context before they
ever reach the lab bench. IDO can be
easily adapted to new cell types and
indications. Using your own data, you
can build models tailored to your
research questions to simulate different
cell types from shape down to genes and
their protein structures, where they end
up in the cell, what they interact with,
and how they affect cellular responses.
>> Wow. This is the foothills of longevity
escape velocity. I've been waiting for
this forever. Alex,
>> medicine is cooked. This is what I'll if
people like the the the catchphrases,
read my lips. Medicine is cooked. This
is what the end of medicine looks like.
It looks like a virtual cell and the
beginning of longevity escape velocity.
Putting the posit I I actually think we
can get probably to LEV without solving
all of medicine. My my bet is it'll be
probably a class of molecules maybe like
fourth or fifth generation uh GLP1s that
that get us to LEV. I think this is
actually a supererset of getting us to
longevity escape velocity. I think this
is like this is how we cure all disease
everywhere. Uh and the the way we do it
is we build a virtual cell. It it's just
like we didn't actually have to solve
human intelligence to solve AGI. It
turns out you can just get AGI from
compressing general human knowledge.
It's not that hard in in principle.
Similarly, I think this is how we solve
all disease. It's not that hard. In
principle, you simply train the world's
best foundation model to model all cell
states uh and all interventions against
cells. And then you do like an alpho
type tree search against possible
interventions to discover how to steer a
virtual cell state from a diseased state
to a healthy state and then generalize
that to tissue and organisms and boom,
you've solved all human disease. I I
think that's like the endame. This is
hyperpersonalized for you, right? You
insert your DNA sequence, all right, and
your current blood chemistries and all
of that. And there's a incilicone model
of your biology and it will tell you
whether this drug works for you or
doesn't. Seline.
>> Yes. But I I I also just on on that, I
don't want to like overromanticize the
personalized aspect. It's an ideal
virtual cell is as personalized for you
as say if you feed a quote unquote
personalized prompt to chat GPT. the
output is personalized for you. Well,
yeah, superficially it's a function of
the inputs, but actually it's a
generalist model.
>> Salem, your thoughts, B?
>> Well, this has been a trend. I'll go
back to the biotech stuff, right? We've
been we've been turning biology into
information. When you turn something
into information, it hops on the
exponential curve. And we're seeing this
uh go through live. uh and the uh the
the you know which each of us have what
50 trillion cells in the human body
right roughly um uh essentially when you
can model that uh essentially a human
being becomes a software engineering
problem and we have really good
techniques to navigate software read
write understand etc etc and the phen
amazing thing for me we've been we've
done a good job in reading you know you
have reading writing comprehension right
when you're trying to learn a new
language in in this case language of
biology. We've done a pretty good job of
reading. We've started to do writing
with crisper and now these mRNA vaccines
etc. This gives us a huge depth into the
comprehension side with the digital
twinning that can take place. So, holy
crap, this opens up the door. Uh I would
go with Alex's comment that uh um
medical is cooked. Emod.
>> Yeah, like this is kind of my hope for
what the Genesis project would be like.
Um, it seems very straightforward to me
now that if we had a Manhattan project
to cure disease through in silicico
massive world human body models, cell
models and organizing all our collective
knowledge on cancer and autism and all
these other things, we will definitely
get a result. Like I'm not even doing
that.
>> It's not going to be a government
program. The labs are going to do that
for us. But I'm like, why don't we
actually get together and get
governments to put into a Manhattan
project type thing and just have a
straight shot at it and make all the
data open? You know, this could be your
point is well taken. At least the
government is sitting on a lot of data.
Uh, and the government could externalize
all the data to the private labs like
CZI and IDO cell and and others who are
all building foundation models like make
it a public good that they can all train
off of a common crawl. Yeah, we've done
that in the UK where you have access to
this. Every government should follow
suit. And this fits with what we talked
about earlier with anthropic. Again,
what are they going to apply their
computation to? They will build a human
cell model. They will build a whole body
model, but I'd prefer for those to be
public goods and us, let's cure cancer.
Let's address all these negative kind of
things and let's understand the body
like never before. Again, that's much
better than building an atom bomb even
because it will have the biggest impact
on humanity ever. Mhm. Dave,
>> well, just for anyone listening who's
not a biotechnologist and they're like,
"Well, I'm not going to build a full
cell simulator. I have no idea how to do
that." You're thinking about it the
wrong way. You heard earlier on the pod
that we're looking at 10,000x expansion
in AI with some other innovations that
could be more like a million x. It's
totally data starved. The full cell
simulator is a way that it can design
thousands or hundreds of thousands of
experiments and get reasonably good test
results back through a simulation rather
than having to run millions of assays.
That also applies in all kinds of other
areas where every investment we've made
in a company like Meror or Macato that
is wrestling with new types of data to
feed the AI, they're thriving and
growing and making money and valuation.
You know, Mor is worth 40 billion or 20
now, 40 by the end of the year. Uh
they're just absolutely killing it. But
every field of endeavor is going to be
data starved. So no matter what you
know, you probably know a field that
needs to supply data back to the great
AI. The full cell simulator is just the
perfect biotech solution, but every
industry has a solution.
>> Yeah.
>> And so competitive, too. I mean, it's
probably worth noting that this is from
a company co-founded by David Baker, who
shared the 2024 Nobel Prize in Chemistry
with Demis for solving protein folding.
This is the next big thing, next grand
challenge arguably in biology/ medicine
after now that structural biology
arguably has been solved. Solve whole
cell simulation and then you're halfway
to solving all disease.
>> Oh, love it. All right. To call out to
our creatives out there, please send us
your outro music videos. We're at a
posity. Send them to media
diamandis.com. Uh we love your outro
videos. Want to see it. Uh, I'll pull
before we go to our AMA. A quick note
again, follow us on X, moonshots_pod.
We're going to be putting out clips and
putting out uh these uh these podcast
recordings on X as well. And join us at
the Moonshot Summit. Go to moonshots.com
to apply. Gentlemen, uh, See and I have
an AMA with the abundance community in 8
minutes. So, I'm going to suggest we
speedrun uh the AMA if you don't mind.
>> We should do the AMA in 8 minutes. We're
going to do the answers. Answers.
>> Yes. Okay.
>> Warm up.
>> All right. Emod, you pick one first.
>> Can't we keep making Frontier models
more energy efficient instead of
building all this new power at Bion 75?
Yep. I mean, that's necessity is the
mother of innovation. As we run out of
energy, as we run out of RAM, you're
going to optimize immensely and it'll be
a big boon for everyone. Salem.
>> Um,
will we see an X-P prize aimed at
solving the electricity supply problem?
We actually proposed in the last
visionary or a couple of visionarians
ago a uh uh enough energy storage
off-rid to keep a village or town um
energy sufficient for 3 days. But it
looks like the market will take care of
that. Yeah.
>> And regulatory is the problem. So it
doesn't really serve as an enterprise
where you need huge technology
breakthrough. This serves better as a
this is a regulatory issue and a market
issue. Dave, over to you.
>> I'll take four. If China has the
advantage on power and the US has the
advantage on chips, who actually has the
real AI advantage? Definitely chips are
uh you know power is a problem but we
need 100 gawatts by the end of the
decade. We already manufacture a
terowatt in the US. So we're 10% of
power will go to AI by the end of the
decade. we'll get that far, then we'll
be really desperate for more power. But
between here and there, it's all about
chips. Every chip, you know, that's why
memory is up 5x. So that's the bigger
advantage in the short run.
>> Yeah. Alex, number two is for you.
>> Number two asks, could interconnected
micro grids popping up everywhere reduce
the load on the main grid enough to
matter? I I think I would invert the
question, invert the premise of the
question. It's it's not that the load on
the main grid is going to be reduced.
It's the exact opposite that there's so
much economic demand for the compute and
the compute needs so much energy. Before
long, unless we fully externalize all of
the compute to orbit and the Dyson
swarm, these data centers are going to
be generating a surplus of energy that
can be pushed back onto the grid and
driving utility prices negative.
>> Yes. I mean, I want to I want to make
that point. You know, if you're arguing
against a data center in your backyard,
you're arguing against lowerc cost
energy and economic advantages for your
community. Please understand that. All
right. Uh uh let's go. Let's start with
you, Alex, on this one.
>> Okay. So, I'll take question number
eight. At the current rate of
improvement, how long until AI is more
efficient per watt than the human brain?
I think we're probably already there. Uh
so, that that's a hot take on this one.
people uh have this maybe like
fetishization uh of the land hour limit
that thinking oh well we we must really
be far away in efficiency per watt from
what biology is able to accomplish.
Biology is actually wildly inefficient.
The our our whole organism uh and and
mammals in general were never optimized
for compute. Whereas silicon uh and CMOS
and whatever comes after CMOS, maybe
it'll be photonix, which I know Dave is
of of interest, it was optimized from
scratch was designed for compute. I
don't think the human brain is as
efficient as many think. And the
argument can be made that actually if
you look at a per watts per task or watt
hours per task basis, the the leading
edge GPUs may actually be already more
efficient than human brains,
>> especially if you take into account the
amount of energy required to train up a
human over the course of 20 years,
right?
>> Yeah. Life lifetime total cost of
ownership as it were.
>> I'll put a pin and a correlary to that
too. Uh people use the power difference
as a way to explain that AI thinking is
very very different from human thinking.
I think that that people will soon
realize that it's not that different at
all. That the power difference will go
away very quickly. But also this like
yeah that's why it's nothing like us
will also gradually go away.
>> Uh I will take number five. Uh what's
actually driving the rush? Why not keep
energy growth at past levels and accept
slower growth from its WHD and DRN?
uh I think the the the easy thing here
is intelligence is looking more and more
like a general purpose input that will
drive economic growth right and so
having saying let's have less
intelligence saying let's have less
electricity or less internet it's it you
want more of it and it improves research
improves drug discoveries we saw all all
today logistics everything so you want
as much of it as possible there's also
competitive pressure if one company
slows down or country then others won't.
So, it's not about accepting that
capacity. You got to get your head
around abund the abundance idea. All the
thing we should be doing is accelerating
energy abundance.
>> All right, Dave.
>> I'll take the easy one. Number seven.
Whatever happened to fuel cells?
Actually, you know, Elon Musk started
his passion in life was ultra capacitors
originally.
>> That was his Stanford thesis before he
dropped out before starting.
>> Well, whatever happened to those too?
What what happened is lithium batteries
worked far far better than anyone ever
would have predicted. and they're still
improving. So, it's sucked all the
capital out of the other ideas. Uh, so
that's all that happened.
>> All right, Emod, close us out here.
>> Yeah, if 71% of Americans oppose data
centers, is this grid buildout actually
going to help regular people's
electricity or just make it scarcer and
more expensive? David Harmon not 03. I
mean, it's what you just said, Peter,
right? It's going to make your
electricity cheaper. More power is good.
These things are not polluting. We need
more data centers. We need more power.
And we need to make sure it's all built
right. Amazing. And you guys did it. You
did it in 8 minutes. Uh, and Sem, we've
got a whole 60 seconds to get over to
our abundance community.
>> I'm going to be two minutes late. I got
to get like some a little bit of food
before you in the meantime. Gentlemen,
Jesus Christ.
>> I love you all so much. This was such a
fun today.
>> Just so much and your brilliance. You
guys are amazing. So, so proud to have
you as our Moonshot mates. Alex, Dave,
Immad, Salem, thank you always. Thank
you to our listeners. Uh we love having
you and hopefully you find this, you
know, a way of keeping up with what's
going on in the world because we are in
an accelerating singularity. Uh and no
time to sleep, no time to blink.
>> Don't take Don't get fatigued like I
did.
>> Yeah.
>> Take care, guys. Be well. All right.
Thanks, Peter.